<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A second memento for magistrates Directing how to reduce all offenders, and beeing reduced, how to preserue them in vnitie and loue both in Church and common wealth. By W.W. Doctor of Diuinity, and one of his Maiesties chaplains in ordinary.</title>
            <title>Obedience or ecclesiasticall union</title>
            <author>Wilkes, William, d. 1637.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 144 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15350</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25634</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114429</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849654</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849654</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14815</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15350)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14815)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1536:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A second memento for magistrates Directing how to reduce all offenders, and beeing reduced, how to preserue them in vnitie and loue both in Church and common wealth. By W.W. Doctor of Diuinity, and one of his Maiesties chaplains in ordinary.</title>
                  <title>Obedience or ecclesiasticall union</title>
                  <author>Wilkes, William, d. 1637.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 73, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted for Roger Iackson, and are to be sold at his shop in Fleet-street neere the Conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Another issue, with cancel title page, of: Wilkes, William.  Obedience or ecclesiasticall union.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Obedience, or ecclesiasticall union.</note>
                  <note>Errata on L3v, final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14815:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14815:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SECOND MEMENTO FOR <hi>Magiſtrates.</hi> Directing how to reduce all offenders, <hi>and beeing reduced, how to preſerue them</hi> in vnitie and loue both in Church and common wealth. <hi>By</hi> W. W. <hi>Doctor of Diuinity, and one of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Chaplains in Ordinary.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Roger Jackson, representing an eagle and eaglet facing the sun over a mountainous landscape (McKerrow 280)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>AT LONDON Imprinted for <hi>Roger Iackſon,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Fleet-ſtreet neere the Conduit: 1608.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14815:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14815:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE HIGH AND Mighty Great Brittaines moſt</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Monarch, <hi>Iames</hi> the <hi>firſt, of France and Ireland King,</hi> defender of the ſaith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt dread Soueraigne:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>GOd which hath put the <hi>Globe</hi> of this <hi>little</hi> world into the hands of your rule, doth in the bottomleſſe <hi>graces</hi> wherewith he hath imbrodered your <hi>Scepter,</hi> merite your thankefuleſt <hi>recognition</hi> of his diuine goodneſſe, in whoſe boſome their <hi>Spring</hi> ariſeth, and oblige the Chriſtian Nations of your <hi>Kingdomes</hi> in ſtraighteſt bonds of <hi>loyaltie</hi> vnto your <hi>Sacred Perſon,</hi> the next and immediate <hi>Conduit</hi> by which all happineſſe is deriued vnto them.</p>
            <p>Your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> religious affections to the ſeruice of God, experienced in thoſe effects of your royall deſires with beſt offices to glorifie his eminent and eternall being,
<pb facs="tcp:14815:3"/> hath a moſt ſure promiſe of bleſsings from the immortall rewarder of holy workes. And for ſo much as your <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie</hi> in your admirable wiſdome ſtudying by all meanes to continuate the tranquill peace of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> hath ſeene it neceſſarie to propoſe, and by intimation of your <hi>gratious</hi> pleaſure inioyned one <hi>vniforme</hi> order of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip due to Gods diuine excellencie. The Subiects of your <hi>Dominions</hi> whoſe toungs are the true witneſſes of their hearts, to acknowledge that <hi>ſupreame Power</hi> which is in exiſtent in your princely rule, will not faile by their cheerefull obedience the <hi>true workemaiſter</hi> of happy <hi>State,</hi> to manifeſt their religion to God, and ſubmiſsion to your iuſt <hi>commaund!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any through a wanton <hi>Superfluitie</hi> of fancie, ſhall diſaccuſtome their deuotiue actions from the traine wherevnto your Lawes would range them: <hi>God</hi> ſhall in time reueale better things vnto their apprehenſion, and by their induſtrie, whom your Maieſtie hath deputed for the adminiſtration of <hi>gouerment,</hi> frame them to that <hi>method</hi> of deuotion which in the <hi>Prerogatiue</hi> of your wiſdome is preſcribed vnto all.</p>
            <p>In meane time, I know he which ſhall oppoſe himſelfe againſt this euill, now growne headdie by cuſtome and ſuffrance of time, lyes open for the racket of mallice to band him into the hazard of vndoing, the thoughts whereof ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded with the knowledge of my owne diſabilitie, to write in a matter of ſo great <hi>conſequence,</hi> had kept me reſolute in my reſolued ſilence, but that my priuate conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience, and ſorrowe to ſee this vnnaturall diſtraction, wherein the body doth refuſe to follow the will of the head, counterpoized the <hi>validitie</hi> of all other oppoſite
<pb facs="tcp:14815:3"/> reſpects, and gaue confidence in your Maieſtie for my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, who hauing nothing better then my ſelfe to beſtow vpon your Maieſtie, do with beſt <hi>alacrity</hi> of ſpirit, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uote and giue my all, to be diſponed at your <hi>Princely</hi> pleaſure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God</hi> which ballanceth the times, prolong the time of your most glorious Regiment, and ſo ſtrengthen your <hi>ſacred power</hi> in the continuance of that vnmatchable goodneſſe, wherewith he hath honoured all your liues time, that when the time of times ſhall come, wherein time ſhall be without time, you may be receiued into his timeleſſe eternitie.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Maieſties</hi> faithfull Subiect <hi>and humble Seruant WILLIAM WILKES.</hi>
               </signed>
               <pb facs="tcp:14815:4"/>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="royal_notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:14815:4"/>
            <head>BY THE KING.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He care which we haue had, and paines which we haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to ſettle the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of this church of England in an vniformitie as wel of doctrine, as of gouernment, both of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agreeable to the word of God, the doctrine of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue church, and the lawes heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore eſtabliſhed for thoſe matters in this realme may ſufficiently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by our former actions, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In the meane time, both they may reſolue either to conforme themſelues to the church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and obey the ſame; or elſe to diſpoſe of themſelues and their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies ſome other waies, as to them
<pb facs="tcp:14815:5"/> ſhall ſeeme meet. And the Biſhops and others whom it concerneth, prouide meete parſons to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes in the place of thoſe who ſhall wilfullie abandon their char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges vpon ſo light cauſes. Aſſuring them that after that day, we ſhall not faile to do that which Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prouidence requireth at our hands. That is to put in execution all wayes and meanes, that may take from among our people all grounds and occaſions of Sects, deuiſions, and vnquietneſſe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of as we wiſh there may neuer be occaſion giuen vs to make proofe, but that this our admonition may haue equall force in all mens hearts to worke an vniuerſall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie. So we doe require all Arch-biſhopps, Byſhopps, and
<pb facs="tcp:14815:5"/> other Eccleſiaſticall parſons, to do their vttermoſt endeauours by conferences, arguments, perſwati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and by all other wayes of loue and gentleneſſe, to reclaime all that be in the Miniſtrie, to the obedience of our Church lawes.</p>
            <p>For which purpoſe onely, we haue enlarged the time former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prefixed for their remoue, or reformation, to the end, that if it bee poſsible, that vniformitie which we deſire, may be wrought by clemencie, and by weight of reaſon, and not by rigour of lawe.</p>
            <p>And the like aduertizement we doe giue to all ciuill Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, Gentlemen, and others of vnderſtanding, as well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in the counties as in Citties
<pb facs="tcp:14815:6"/> and Townes, requiring them alſo not in any ſort to ſupport, fauour, or countenance any ſuch factious Miniſters in their obſtinacy. Of whoſe indeauours we doubt not but ſo good ſucceſſe may follow as this our Admonition with their indeauours may preuent the vſe of any other meanes to retaine our people in their due <hi>obedience</hi> to vs, and in <hi>vnitie</hi> of minde to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of Almightie God.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Giuen at our Mannor of Ottlands</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 16. <hi>day of Iuly</hi> 1604. <hi>in the ſecond yeare of our raigne of England, France and Ireland, And of Scotland the xxxvii.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline> 
               <hi>God ſaue the King.</hi>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:14815:6"/>
            <head>OBEDIENCE Or Eccleſiaſticall Vnion.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E haue now long time been more diſputant, then agent in <hi>Religion.</hi> and whereas we ſhould ſtudy to doe what we know, we are ſet in <hi>inquiſition</hi> to finde, what we may beleeue.</p>
            <p>Such is the ſupple, and reſtleſſe <hi>volubilitie</hi> of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering mindes, whoſe licentious feruour, will not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſtrength to ground and ſettle them in dutifull <hi>obedience</hi> vnto a ſtayed rule: That there is no Errour ſo abſurd, but ſome doe imbrace it; No <hi>Paradox</hi> ſo incredulous, but ſome doe beleeue it; no <hi>Action</hi> ſo irreligious, but ſome doe countenance it; not any <hi>Sentence</hi> ſo certaine, but ſome by contradiction, doe call it into needleſſe and ſubtile <hi>diſpute.</hi> That which wrought much hurt amongſt the auncient Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <note place="margin">Procopius lib. 3. Goth.</note> hath greatly troubled the <hi>State</hi> preſent, and would dangerouſlie hazard the gouernment both of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common-weale,</hi> if Princely <hi>determination</hi> had not preuented it.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:14815:7"/>
            <p>\ To diſpute, and by triall of diſputation to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the weake, as <hi>Saint Paule</hi> did with the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans at <hi>Troada:</hi> or to conuince the <hi>errant,</hi> as the <hi>Saints</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act 20, Euſeb eccl. hiſt. lib. 6. cap. 24. Trip. lib. 1. cap. 11.</note> did; <hi>Auguſtine</hi> with <hi>Poſcentius: Sabinus</hi> with <hi>Photi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> and <hi>Origen</hi> with <hi>Berillus:</hi> or to determine things doubtfull, as the religious and graue reuerend <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> did in their councels and Synods; or to ſettle the Peace of the Church as in the <hi>colloqui at Ratiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonn</hi> 
               <note place="margin">An. 1541. An. 1603. Ia. 14.</note> appointed by <hi>Charles</hi> the fift; and it pleaſed his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> in the late interlocutorie conſerence, with the <hi>Lords, Biſhops,</hi> &amp; others of the clergie, at <hi>Hampton</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Auſt. lib. 2. cap. 13. &amp; 14. contr. Creſcon.</note> 
               <hi>Court,</hi> hath alwaies had ſpeciall approbation.</p>
            <p>But yet (if I may in the libertie of a humble ſpirit, freely ſpeake, what ſome of you, (the <hi>Bretheren</hi> of the <hi>newfangled</hi> faction) in the merite of your conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious diſpoſition ſhould patiently heare) to liue in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to orders, orderly by iudgment of deciſion eſtabliſhed, is more anſwerable to faith, profitable for the Church, and honourable for our calling.</p>
            <p>By the firſt, we bring light to the truth, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme knowledge: by the ſecond, we giue life to the truth, and after our example direct others in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious ſeruice of God; a dutie amongſt all Offices appertaining to man, moſt excellent and moſt deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; whether we conſider the bottomleſſe graces wherwith Heauens hand hath embrodered our ſtate in general; or vnfould before our ſelues, the vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able bleſſings he hath enfolded vpon vs in particuler.</p>
            <p>My priuate life hath giuen me the right hand of Opportunitie, to read what hath been diſputed, and finding the chriſtian cauſe become more contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14815:7"/> for that the rules of Gouerment haue beene ſo diſputable, doe (without all partiall conſtruction of what I haue read) in ſingleneſſe of heart, wiſh that the ſpirit of ſingularity in ſome particulars of you, giuing place vnto publicke Iudgement, had rather by dutious actions conformed it ſelfe vnto Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, then by vniuſt oppoſition, endeauoured for li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious libertie.</p>
            <p>Action is the beſt blazoner of vertues vertue; The trueſt approuer of Learnings value. The ſoundeſt witneſſe of hearts deſire; and then worthy principall acceptation. When it worketh by the Line not of opinion, but of Iudgement: not of priuate fancie, but of publicke rule; patternd vnto vs in the lawes both of God and men.</p>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>§. 2.</head>
               <p>The iuſt conſtitutions of lawfull Princes, are the ſetled boundaries of duty vnto their Subiects, and doe confine euery man within the liſts of his parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular obedience, as the land-markes in the fields doe limmit out their inheritance; He which <note n="*" place="margin">Deutr. 27.</note> remoued theſe was held accurſed. Conſider I pray you whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he who vncharitably offendeth againſt thoſe, can in his offence be reputed bleſſed.</p>
               <p>The determinations of God, are the vncontroul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able warrants of power vnto Princes. The infallable rules both of their duty vnto the higheſt ruler, and authoritie ouer the greateſt that are ruled.</p>
               <p>Rules made knowne vnto them, not ſo much by the dim light of nature, as by the euerlaſting director
<pb facs="tcp:14815:8"/> of holy actions, in the euidence of Scripture, wherein are the trulie honourable inſtructions for higher powers to commaund their ſubiects, and moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt directions for Subiects to obey higher powers.</p>
               <p>Vnto the King it is a patterne and carde to guide <note place="margin">Auſtin. lib. de vera re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig. cap. 31. vida. lib. 2. de Reip. dignit.</note> by; vnto the Subiects it is a light wherewith to iudge aright of the lawes vnder which they liue. So that whatſoeuer is good in the lawes of Princes, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable in the dutie of ſubiects. That ſame is as it were coppied out of, and iuſtified by the eternall lawe of God, by whoſe powerfull grace <hi>Kings</hi> doe raigne, and by whoſe gratious influence <hi>Princes</hi> doe <note place="margin">Sap. 7.</note> decree righteouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>If you had made this lawe the chiefe head and principall ruler of your actions, and held it ſo ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary in your thoughts, as it was common in your talke; it would haue bred in your religious mindes, a dutifull eſtimation of Princely offices, and made you reſpectiue of publicke obſeruances, if your mindes be religious, this being an <hi>Axiom</hi> inuinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that nothing is more auncient in the lawes of God; nothing more pregnant to aduance common good, then <hi>obedience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, to God, the ſupreame guide of this worldes maſſe, to whoſe ſoueraigne power all fleſh muſt ſtoope, and to whoſe will all kingdomes doe owe conformitie, in that he requireth.</p>
               <p>Secondly, to the King, ſent of God to be the <note n="*" place="margin">Rex dei figuram in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter homines repreſentat. Diotogines lib. de reg.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenter of his Maieſtie, and the <note n="†" place="margin">Plutar. li de doctr. principis.</note> 
                  <hi>Leutenant</hi> of his regencie.</p>
               <p>The memorie of which ſubordination, as it ſerueth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14815:8"/> to drownd all ſelfe conceipt, that may hold the <hi>King</hi> with admiration of his ſublimitie, and ſtrengthen him againſt all aduerſary meanes which interrupt him in the exerciſe of that high dutie, the deuine goodneſſe requireth of him: So it doth <hi>(obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to God preſerued)</hi> binde vs generallie, without exception, and particularlie, without reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to obay him, cheerefully, without cunctation, and readily without inquiſition, what he ought or may commaund vs to doe, whether it be in cauſes <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> or <hi>Ciuill.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>§. 3.</head>
               <p>That Princes may commaund the obſeruation and practiſe of religion in their Realmes, domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and kingdomes, according as God informeth their conſciences by the direction of his <hi>alteaching</hi> ſpirit, and rules of his ſacred worde, in the hands of thoſe Prieſts, whoſe lippes he hath ſanctified, to be the treaſuries of his wiſdome, is by the vnited prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of all common-weales, manifeſtly conuinced, and hath euidence in the teſtimonies of the beſt common-wealths-men.</p>
               <p>Amongſt all things incident into the actions of men, there is none more excellent, then Religion ſaith <note n="a" place="margin">In Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenide.</note> 
                  <hi>Plato:</hi> In it, our cheefeſt good conſiſteth, ſaith <note n="b" place="margin">Lib. 3. cap. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Lactantius:</hi> It is the vnmoueable foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Princely honour, ſaith <note n="c" place="margin">Lib. de recta ſide ad Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſium.</note> 
                  <hi>Cyrill.</hi> The ſafeſt defence of publicke ſtate, ſaith <note n="d" place="margin">De con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptione digeſtoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> 
                  <hi>Iuſtinian.</hi> The richeſt ſtore-houſe of mans felicitie, ſaith <note n="e" place="margin">Neceph. lib. 7. ca. 46</note> 
                  <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine.</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:14815:9"/> And therefore ought to be the <note n="f" place="margin">Inter cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teras ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudines quas amor publi. us preuigili nobis cura indixit, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipuam im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratoriae maieſtatis curam eſſe perſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. verae religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis indagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. lib. le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell. tit. 2.</note> cheefeſt care of Maieſties <hi>Empire,</hi> ſaith <hi>Valentinian.</hi> In deed moſt worthy to be the higheſt care of all cares appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to Pincely rule, both in reſpect of the <hi>Prince</hi> and of the People.</p>
               <p>In reſpect of the <hi>Prince,</hi> for by religion, and <note n="*" place="margin">Rex orat habita in Senat.</note> workes according therevnto, God is moued to giue life vnto their councels, perfection to their indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, and ſettlement to their throanes; for which cauſe, the more eminent they are in regall Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the more vigilant they ought to be in religious pietie.</p>
               <p>In reſpect of the People, for that the happineſſe of our liues doth primarily and principally conſiſt in the well ordering of our liues, according to the rule of his will who did at the firſt imbreath life. And when our wills doe yeeld to the regiment of his will, whoſe ſeruice ought to haue the higheſt care of all cares, appertaining to this life. Wee are ſure to reeaue at his mercifull hands, all things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie for the conſeruation of life, his prouidence to guide it, his wiſdome to inſtruct it, his patience to ſupport it, and mercy to prouide for it, with that fatherly affection, which affordeth his creatures to ſerue, and Angels to guarde vs. All which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiues our liues enioy, like ſo many Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of his loue, giuen by the influence of <hi>grace</hi> to make them happy, as the obſeruation of Pietie doth approue them to be holy.</p>
               <p>So is Religion to vs, the toppe of all publicke good. To the <hi>King,</hi> the moſt valued ſacrifice of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14815:9"/> reingration to God, both to the <hi>King</hi> and vs, the beſt aſſurance of our ſecular happineſſe; and moſt ſufficient remonſtrance of celeſtiall bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p>In the acknowledged knowledge whereof his <note place="margin">Procla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 24. Octo. 1603</note> 
                  <hi>Maieſtie</hi> knowing no greater meanes then Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to make euident the ſight of heauen, and in the iudgement both of men and <hi>Angells,</hi> his thanks to God, and loue to vs, amongſt all negotiations of State dependant vpon his charge; ſithence the <hi>Imperiall</hi> Crowne of this Realme deſcended vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, <hi>(Committing his owne priuate)</hi> laboured, firſt to ſettle the affaires of Religion, and ſeruice of God; his ſole Soueraigne Lord, by whoſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly goodneſſe he holdes the Royalties of his prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiues, the excellencie of his calling, the ſecuritie of his content, the prerogatiue of his ſecurity, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of his kingdomes.</p>
               <p>Secondly, to reforme (not the State of the <note place="margin">Procla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 16. Iuly. 1604.</note> Church, formerly by Lawe eſtabliſhed, as if in any materiall point hee had found it defectiue) but the troubleſome ſpirit of ſome perſons whoſe onely contentment reſteth, in the proſecutions of their owne fantaſies, and by his iudiciall authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, made knowne in his admonitorie declarations, to enrayle thoſe partes of our Chriſtian duties, which noueltie with diſdaine of Antiquity had li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſly violated.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:14815:10"/>
               <head>§. 4.</head>
               <p>Wherein as his Highneſſe hath giuen vs many ſingular Teſtimonies and euident aſſurances of his Princely reſolution, what reaſon haue (you of the faction) now that his Highneſſe hath deliberated, and vpon deliberation promulged the dutie which each part ſhall performe, to refuſe the dutie impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? What iuſt and ſufficient cauſe are yee able to alleadge wherefore you ſhould not abſolutely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcend in this buſineſſe, to haue your opinions ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled by his definitiue ſentence?</p>
               <p>You cannot miſdoubt the ſufficiencie of his Iudgement, thereof you haue already receiued ſo good a taſte, as that you confeſſe him, (he thankes <note place="margin">Humble petition.</note> you for it) able of himſelfe to iudge the equitie of your cauſe.</p>
               <p>I will not wrong you ſo much as to thinke that you make any Queſtion of his, either <note n="a" place="margin">Leges ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t public. vitae praecepta quibus nos omnes ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporare ſemper op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portet, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> omne bonum &amp; equitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perpetuo ſpectant at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ab eo qui iubendi &amp; exeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di poteſtatem habet, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponuntur. Bieſius lib. quart de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub.</note> 
                  <hi>Authoritie</hi> to commaund, or power to execute what he doth commaund. The whole body of this realme, and euery particuler member thereof, either in perſon, or repreſentation, haue with one full voyce of tongue, and heart, acknowledged his rightfull So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigntie, and their obleaged dutie, vnto the laſt expence of bloud, ſo that vnleſſe <hi>Obedience</hi> be in your mouthes, as Iuſtice ſome-time is, in the mouth of a Lawyer, and not as it ought to be, in your harts, and affections, you will not like blaſted Branches fall from that body; but with genuine Submiſſion
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14815:10"/> (not diſtracted by ouer-pleaſing ſeruice of your ſelues, nor mollified, with that too much reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſelfe conceipt,) referre your liues to his Lawes; your deſires to his will: and your opinion, to his iudgement.</p>
               <p>If you conſider his lawes, herein he hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed ſuch godly care that we may ſay of them not as <hi>Polydore</hi> did of the conquerors: <hi>Magis ſunt ex vſu Principis quam populi:</hi> But as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſayd of the Lawes of <hi>Iſraell:</hi> There is no Nation ſo great that hath ordinances, and lawes ſo righteous, this being the cheefeſt endeauour of his Highneſſe deſire, to haue the workes of Religion reuerendly performed, the cauſes of his Subiects, vprightly determined; and the Iudgments of his <hi>Kingdome</hi> euenly ballan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. All which are actions of moſt high and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable merite, wherevnto the hearts of mightie <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> ought continually to be faſhioned.</p>
               <p>Of theſe premiſes (if you will ſpare me the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt of moſt) and let ſome one, or other good-man, if you will, make illation, beholde, the man that was ſo diſcourſiue vpon the method of <hi>Obedience.</hi> (Good-man he was, and you reputed him for a good-man,) doth in the zeale of that reformation you deſire, conclude, that to diſobay a <hi>King,</hi> ſo compleat in all princely indowments: ſo wiſe, in councelling: ſo powerfull in commanding; ſo reſpectiue of publike good, and deuotiue to the ſeruice of God, muſt needs be condemned forwicked and vngodly rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, <note place="margin">Pag. 114.</note> And (if you pleaſe to make him Iudge in the action) deſerueth iuſtly to receaue Gods puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <note place="margin">Pag. 112.</note>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:14815:11"/> which as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> threatneth is damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>§. 5.</head>
               <p>You doe not I hope thinke your ſelues exempted from the inbarment of this pollicie, that you ſhould as men lawleſſe with ſo ſtrong oppoſition, refuſe to be guided by his lawes. They are the wings vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which the good doe flie; They are the yoakes vnder which the euill doe labour: Well borne minds will not deny them, well bredde men will readily accept them, And free generous ſpirits en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour conformitie with them.</p>
               <p>If you will bee free, obaye the Lawe; If you take awaye the Lawe, you take away liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, we <note n="*" place="margin">Libertas aufertur, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lato iure ac legibus: Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oniſius Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licar. lib. 7.</note> therefore obaye the Lawe that wee may be free. <note n="†" place="margin">Cicero in oratione pro Aulo Cluentio.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Free, not to doe what we liſt, <note n="a" place="margin">Nullus ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus priuatus, reru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſura eſt. Plato. nec libido. Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripides.</note> Luſt is no line to leuell libertie, nor was fancie at any time the true meaſure of duetie. But free to doe what reaſon ſhall by publick Ordinations enioyne; which becauſe they are common to all, (although the Lawe of the <note n="b" place="margin">Lex Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andri Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratoris.</note> 
                  <hi>Empire</hi> doe free Princes from the ſolemnities and formalities of them). His High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe doth with Princely reſolution, and you ſhould with <note n="c" place="margin">Salomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius li. 1. de principatu.</note> reuerend admiration, acknowledge them for the rules of your actions.</p>
               <p>If you yeeld then that <hi>Obedience</hi> which in iuſtice they exact, and peruerſneſſe onely will denye, you ſhall be imbraced as men rightly indenized
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14815:11"/> in Loyalties prerogatiue. But ſo long as you ſtand out againſt them, that <hi>Obedience</hi> hath her let, and incompatebilitie with you, your tumultarie Agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions will giue you the imputation of diſloyaltie to the <hi>King,</hi> repugnance to order, and enmitie to the Church, which requireth your zealous labour to maintaine it, with the religious imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of your vertuous and peaceable endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoures.</p>
               <p>Plead not <hi>exemption,</hi> when the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> placeth euery ſoule vnder ſubiection: Yee are, queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe yee are, marſhalled within the liſtes of this order, and whatſoeuer Priuiledge you aſſume vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your ſelues, you haue in this, no pre-eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie aboue others, but are with like bands ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto Soueraigntie: Pleaſeth it you to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe your thoughts from the opinion which poſſeſſeth you, and entertaine your ſtudies, with thoſe fore-gone Examples of religious Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men before time. You may in their liues, (and <note place="margin">Baſil. epiſt. prima.</note> the hiſtories of Gods <hi>Saints,</hi> are the liuely exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Gods common-wealths,) as in a Gallarie of pleaſant Pictures, ſee the viue Images of loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſpirites, conforming them-ſelues with all ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; <hi>Aaron</hi> to <hi>Moſes; Zadocke</hi> to <hi>Salomon; Gregory</hi> to <hi>Maurilius,</hi> &amp;c. Reuerend Prieſts to their lawfull <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> as they haue proceeded in Church buſineſſe.</p>
               <p>You may ſee the holy conſort of Gods deuotiues, with all humilitie defraying the tribute of their moſt due ſeruice to heauens Maieſtie, not as fancie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, but as the authoritie of their Superiours,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14815:12"/> (ſtrengthened with his power who hath ſoueraigne ſuperioritie in all cauſes) preſcribed.</p>
               <p>You may ſee the Chriſtian armies and Souldiers, ſacred vnto the ſeruice of our bleſſed Sauiour, in the diſſemination of his euerlaſting truth, though equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in vnitie of Ordination, and vnited in miniſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all equallitie, yet performing their humble and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous obedience, to them of their owne ſocietie, whom only Order, the preſeruer of all things had differenced in dignitie.</p>
               <p>You may ſee our fatherly guides-men of honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable place, auncient yeares, &amp; reuerend behauiour, gathered together in <hi>Counſells</hi> and <hi>Synods</hi> (the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of diuine Ordination to ſtrengthen our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall commerce with the free vſe of ſacred conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations) aduiſing vpon, and preſcribing orders, for the Propagation of religious doctrine, and eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of holy diſcipline.</p>
               <p>All which their <hi>ſacred</hi> reſolutions and holy ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, were no ſooner intimated vnto the Chriſtian world; but you may ſee them with vnqueſtionable <hi>obedience</hi> receiued by <hi>Princes,</hi> as rules of their deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, regarded by <hi>Prieſts,</hi> as the <hi>Canons</hi> of their prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique religion, and followed by the People, as the lights of their Chriſtian conuerſation.</p>
               <p>What the reuerend Fathers of the Church de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed then, was as much reuerenced by the beſt <hi>Princes,</hi> as the beſt decrees of our reuerend Fathers now, are baſely contemned by the worſe <hi>Subiects,</hi> (and with you of the faction) the perſwaſion of your owne ſufficiencie, to know and performe the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14815:12"/> dutie which doth moſt fit you in your perochiall <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidences</hi> hath made them the more contemptible.</p>
               <p>I know that Nature hath intereſſed euery perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular of you, <note n="a" place="margin">Qui libet eſt rei ſuae moderator, rector &amp; arbitrer. in le. in re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mandata mandati. Lex reſpicit ordinem ad bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin. lib. 2. q. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> with abilitie to preſcribe rules vnto your ſelues, in your priuate actions; but thoſe rules are not lawes to binde others, becauſe they haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect more to your owne priuate, then reference to the publicke good; and Natures ſelfe, which hath preuiledged you with ſuch prerogatiue, doth diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>null the libertie, if your rules be repugnant to the lawes of <hi>Superiours:</hi> which giues me hope, you will make no more appeales from your <hi>Ordinaries</hi> vnto your ſelues, but as men conformed to better aduiſe, accept directions from our graue <hi>Prelates,</hi> the moſt competent iudges of decencie in this caſe, and with ſobrietie performe the Offices of your Miniſtrie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the preſcript of holy rule.</p>
               <p>It is ſafer to leaue the <hi>Paines</hi> of your conduct vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lawe, then vnto libertie; and more honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to order your deſignes with correſpondencie to a ſtayed rule, then irregularlie to worke by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript of fancie, the mutuall impartment of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <note place="margin">Iohannes de Turre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cremata.</note> ciuillitie, being then moſt rightly adminiſtred when it is communicated by the line and leuell of Iuſtice.</p>
               <p>Wherefore ſith it hath pleaſed God to endue you with capacitie of diſcourſe, and make you not ſeruilely ſubiect to commaund, as beaſts: but volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 15.</note> inclinable to reaſons dictates, as men; doe not ſuffer affection ſtubbornly to carry you away, but (as you are men of iudgement,) when iudgment doth
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14815:13"/> not giue order and direction for the producement of your actions, diſtaſte the very Propenſion that leads you vnto the action.</p>
               <p>Queſtionleſſe you could not walke in this way of ſingularitie, nor ſo irkeſomely contend for things ſo much prohibited, but that you permitte your vnderſtanding too much reflexe vpon your ſelues, and who will maruaile when the admiration of your owne skill ſhall holde you, if the conceipt of your <hi>obedience</hi> be drowned in your owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt. But you are the true <hi>Philodoxes</hi> of your owne opinions, and will I ſuppoſe rather hazard an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the Good of the Church, and peace of the Countrie, then haue your zeale guided by the limmits of any lawes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>§. 6.</head>
               <p>The more eye-full ought you the ciuill Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates to be ouer this creeping and incroaching euill, that errour by <hi>Schiſme</hi> breake not, what truth by authoritie hath builded.</p>
               <p>To preſerue the peace of the Church is a ſpeciall prerogatiue belonging to the <hi>ſupreame</hi> power of the higheſt commander: and all be it in his <hi>Royall</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon there be great excellencies, (his Princely minde being enriched with ſo many heroicke and diuine vertues) yet becauſe one, as one cannot poſſibly gouerne many, his <hi>Highneſſe</hi> hath with <hi>Kingly</hi> indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence communicated part of this royaltie with you, and inſtiled you <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of peace, that the mention
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14815:13"/> of your names may put you in minde of your du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for the conſeruation of peace <note n="a" place="margin">Sicut vita in homine, ita pax in regno, &amp; ſic ſanitas nihil eſt niſi tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perantia humoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſic pax eſt cum vnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-quod<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> retinet or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem ſuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et ſicut re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedente ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate tendit homo ad interitum? Sic diſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente pace regnum tendit ad deſolatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, vnde vltimum quod atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur pax eſt. Vnde Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus inquit ſicut medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, ad ſani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem ſic defenſor reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. tendere debet ad pacem. Aquin in mat. cap 12</note> without which if ſo be it were poſſible that all other complements of common good might be had in their full perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, neuertheleſſe the common-wealth that ſhould poſſeſſe them, diuorced from concord, could be but a <hi>ſpectacle</hi> of commiſeration. Euen as that body which adorned with ſundry admirable helpes, wanteth health the chiefeſt thing that nature de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Proſperitie</hi> honoureth Peace as her <hi>parent,</hi> and the proſperous peace of all well ordered common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weales, doth acknowledge religion for her cheefeſt ſtaye, as well in regarde of that bleſſed protection which Gods mercifull hand beſtoweth vpon them, who faithfully ſerue him, as alſo for the ſeruiceable diſpoſition which <hi>Religion</hi> worketh both in the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours, and them that are gouerned.</p>
               <p>When they from whoſe habilities the duties of commaund and ſeruice proceed, doe with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant reſolution of minde, acknowledge Heauens diuine <hi>Empire</hi> ouer all, and with aſſured confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence repoſe in the aſſiſtance of God Almightie, that inflameth them which are in place of authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie with deſire to reſemble God in the action of common good, and humbleth inferiours with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence to acknowledge their rule by whoſe indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious labours the <hi>Riuers</hi> of that good are ſet open vnto the comminaltie.</p>
               <p>It qualifieth the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> to rule with conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, in the dread of his iudgement, whoſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14815:14"/> prouidence is the producer of order; it maketh the ſubiect for conſcience, willing to obay, fearing the ſeueritie of diuine reuenge, which followeth them that are wilfully diſobedient vnto <hi>order.</hi> So conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the daughter of Religion, keepes them both, awefull to ſwarue from that which is right, &amp; makes them diligent obſeruers of all effectuall furtherances of the Churches peace, the ſure conſeruatorie of <hi>kingdomes</hi> happineſſe.</p>
               <p>For which cauſe, the beſt common-wealths men, alwayes had in deteſtation this bitter ſtrife and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uying, whatſoeuer the differences were, from whence it did ariſe, and with ſpeciall care endeuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a vniuerſall and vniforme agreement in religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The vnited and monacord practiſe, wherof, hath the happy condition of publicke ſocietie, ſo cloſlie wouen into it, that neither can be, where both are not.</p>
               <p>If I ſhould indeauour the illuſtration of this, by matching it with the contrary in former ſucceſſion of ages, I could produce many fearefull miſeries, which both Church and common-weale, haue ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the reſtleſſe affections of diſagreeing mindes in matters of this kinde.</p>
               <p>Pleaſeth it you, to ſet before your eyes, the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe wherewith the Weſterne Church of olde, <note place="margin">Proclam. in Scotl. 1582</note> and our late neighbour Church (now by a moſt bleſſed vnion moſt happily incorporated) hath been perplexed by the ſame plauſible and faire pretenſes, you ſhall finde iuſt cauſe to feare, leaſt your readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to fauour proceedings of ſuch conſequence,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14815:14"/> ſhall cauſe this <hi>kingdome</hi> to feele thoſe euills <note n="*" place="margin">Facilius impeditur acquirendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatur ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitum. ff. de his quae ſunt ſui vel alien.</note> which hereafter cannot be ſo eaſily remedied, as by your wiſdom now they may be timely preuented.</p>
               <p>You cannot but ſee what hatred this difference in opinion concerning the complements of Church actions, hath already cauſed amongſt many, both of the Cleargie and Laytie.</p>
               <p>Do you not ſee what oppoſition, what diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, what diuiſion hath growne from this varietie, what paſſions haue beene ſtirred, what quarrels pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, what diſgraces offered with mutuall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change to eyther party; what <hi>petitions</hi> haue beene framed? what companies aſſembled? what lawleſſe priuate ſubſcriptions required againſt ſubſcription lawfull and publicke? what parts haue beene taken? what conceipts vrged, and calumniations ſuggeſted, no leſſe to ſtop the ſtreame of the <hi>Lawe,</hi> then to take away all ornaments of comlineſſe, and meanes of difference in <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> order?</p>
               <p>Seeing theſe inconueniences, you muſt needs ſee, that a continuing diſtance of <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> will occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on through continuing variance of <hi>mindes,</hi> continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all hatred, the mother of <hi>ſedition,</hi> the mother of <hi>tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult,</hi> the mother of <hi>inſurrection,</hi> the mother of <hi>depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation</hi> and <hi>ruine.</hi> Wherefore that you may with leſſe trouble preuent a more ſtirring and actuall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, ſhew your ſpeciall care to appeaſe the diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance, ſuffer not miſchiefe to grow to head by your heedleſſe regarde, or priuate <hi>ſupportation</hi> of theſe too familier euils, but doe your vttermoſt endeuours to remoue theſe bitter <hi>Antipathyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:14815:15"/>
               <p>\ In time <hi>(Gentlemen)</hi> in time, in time, leaſt when the bridle of <hi>Obedience</hi> is broken, and the <hi>plumes</hi> of Pride haue mounted <hi>newfangliſme</hi> ſo high, that it both can and will, eyther by fraude ouer-reache, or <hi>power</hi> ouer-beare the Lawes wherevnto it ſhould be ſubiect, you labour in vaine to cure the <note place="margin">Annoſa paſſio me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to momenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neo non curatur.</note> wound; <hi>Old ſoares are not eaſily cured.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So long as the blithfulneſſe of your aſpect reflex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vpon them, they will indeauour ſo much as in them lyeth, quite and cleane to banniſh from their cogitation, all that may ſound vnto <hi>conformity.</hi> But if you with-drawe your hand, and leaue their actions vnwitneſſed by your <hi>Liberalitie</hi> (which is well knowne to haue drawne drye the fountaines of ſome mens wealth) for ſuch mens ſuſtenance and reliefe, they will follow the things which now they ſhunne, and more ceremoniouſly performe the function which belongs to this preheminence.</p>
               <p>Truth will not permit them to be ſo ignorant, as they would, and the want of your ſide propts, will make them ſtudye to goe vpright as they ought, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>If they had not in ſome places receiued ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie Teſtimonies of affection from ſome of you, their indeauours had long ſince moultred betweene their fingers, whether thoſe ſome haue affected and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed this courſe, in deſire to vpholde <hi>oppoſition</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Biſhops,</hi> or to ſeize one the remaining patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of holy religion, I haue not attained ſo perfect a ſight, that I ſhould enter into your <hi>breaſts,</hi> where lod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth the knowledge of your wil &amp; worth. But I feare
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14815:15"/> and would God I might but feare, leaſt that theſe which doe ſo earneſtly ſollicite for <hi>Innouation,</hi> and perſwade the change of a knowne olde good, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pretence of a new better, doe leuell at nothing more then that all things in this ſettled <hi>State,</hi> being diſorderly hudled, themſelues may glide through, whilſt others doe fiſhe in the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled waters.</p>
               <p>An <hi>Action</hi> of ſuch generall deteſtation in the eye of euery wiſe vnderſtanding heart, and of ſuch eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall preiudice to <hi>peace-able</hi> gouernement, that I liſt not to caſte the leaſt aſperſion of ſuch ſtaifull <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie</hi> vpon any of you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Opinion</hi> it ſelfe, in ſome <hi>Newfangliſts</hi> (both <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticke</hi> and <hi>Layicke,</hi> bewitcht with ſtronge in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantments,) labours vnder the countenance of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred vnto <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> without any more ceremonie to impoueriſh the Church of her <hi>Princely</hi> endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and diſable <hi>Maieſtie</hi> in the preſcription of Orders for Churches rule: And ſith their labours could not ſo long continue, but as they are the markes of <hi>faction,</hi> and inſtruments of deuiſion; The <hi>King</hi> (who is the head of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> from whoſe power Authoritie is deriued vnto you, his ſubal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne and ſubordinate both <hi>Iuſtices</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates)</hi> hath with ſpeciall words required you, to afforde no ſupportation vnto the factious miniſters of that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched opinion.</p>
               <p>Peacefull rule, is more pleaſefull to him, and when you pleaſe, to yeelde the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this required ſeruice which you duely
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14815:16"/> owe him, their <hi>ſubmiſsion</hi> vnto that rule, whereby our deuotiue actions in the ſeruice of God are to be framed, will crowne his Princely <hi>regiment</hi> with a bleſſed <hi>vnion</hi> of wils, and conſent of deſires betwixt God and our ſelues.</p>
               <p>The breache of this <hi>vnion</hi> makes a breache of peace, by ſcandall in deed, contention in ſpeach, and <hi>Schiſme</hi> in outward behauiour, a ſinne <note n="a" place="margin">S. Tho 22. q 39. ar. 2. ad. 13.</note> of all ſinnes which may be againſt our neighbour moſt hurtfull, and the <note n="b" place="margin">S. Auſtin. lib. 2 de bap. cap. 6.</note> greateſt, becauſe it is againſt the good of the multitude; ſo that you muſt <note n="c" place="margin">Edw. 3. An. 1.</note> needs acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it to be within your <hi>warde:</hi> and as in your quarter <hi>Seſsions</hi> you <note n="d" place="margin">Mai. Fitſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>harb.</note> ought, in your priuate <hi>Seſsions</hi> you may enquite of offences in this cauſe commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>§. 7.</head>
               <p>And fith that you of the <hi>Graund-Iuries,</hi> together with the <hi>Church-wardens,</hi> in your ſeuerall places, haue the inquiſition of theſe things giuen vnto you in charge. If you be perſwaded rhe cauſe why you were firſt <hi>inſtituted,</hi> was that the truth might haue the better euidence: if you knowe that you are cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to be inſtruments of truth, that you are <hi>intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencers</hi> for the common-wealth, that you are the eares and eyes of <hi>Iuſtices</hi> and <hi>Ordinaries.</hi> If you marke how the lawes concerning theſe matters of the Church, are opened before you, and openly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen you in charge, at the times both of <hi>viſitation</hi> and <hi>Seſsion,</hi> to the end, not onely your ſelues may be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14815:16"/> truly enformed, but euery other which heareth it, may with <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Angels</hi> witneſſe with, or againſt you. Take heed I beſeech you how you neglect ſo great a dutie.</p>
               <p>My eare did tell my ſoule a wonder, when it heard that in ſuch a ſetled <hi>State,</hi> neither the <hi>Biſhop</hi> in his <hi>viſitation,</hi> nor the <hi>Iuſtices</hi> in their <hi>Seſsions,</hi> could (for theſe many yeares) haue notice giuen them of ſuch <hi>exorbitancie,</hi> either by preſentment or indite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>But know, ô know, that when you lay your hands vpon the ſacred booke, to teueale vnto Iuſtice what is done amiſſe, to the end that iudgment might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it. The concealment of theſe miſdone things ſhall be more deare to you, then the <hi>penaltie</hi> can be greeuous to the partie indicted, or preſented; for by you, the partie delinquent may looſe his mortall and fading both goods and liuings: but you fill your liues with ſhame, your ſtate with danger, your names with ignomie, your houſes with bloud, your hearts with diſtruſt, and forfeit your Soules which by oath you haue pawnd to Gods diuine iuſtice.</p>
               <p>But poore ſoules, the motiue cauſe of this offence by concealment of things indictable and preſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, is not in your ſelues; it is the pleaſure of your ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers which doth carry you as the winde doth driue Feathers which way they pleaſe, and ambition of your <hi>Paſtors,</hi> who to couer their owne faults, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controulably to continue their faultfull practiſe, doe labour to make you without conſcience, as Idolls without ſence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:14815:17"/>
               <head>§. 8.</head>
               <p>The more worthy blame are you (the aſſociates of this <hi>Newfangled</hi> faction) to miſlead poore decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſoules into ſuch vnhallowed actions. Diſpence with their oaths you cannot, and how you will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them of <hi>periurie</hi> I ſee not.</p>
               <p>You hoodwinke your ſimple agents with faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of glozing ſpeaches, and beare them in hand, that ſuch and ſuch Articles ſhall not be giuen them in charge. And haue you indeed at any time inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> or compounded with his <hi>Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celour</hi> or <hi>Archdeacon,</hi> to limmit the charge which they giue (according to the preſcript of your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent)? then haue you receaued too much fauour of them, who haue leaſt reaſon to allow diſorder. And it may be truly ſayd, ſuch halfe-waking <hi>Gouernours,</hi> haue giuen you, both hart and hand to croſſe the <hi>Lawe</hi> in practiſe, with the practiſe of your lawes in deuiſe, how euer you haue complotted with them, The <hi>King</hi> is little beholding to you, or them.</p>
               <p>For eyther ſuch <hi>Guardians</hi> of the <hi>ſpiritualties</hi> doe follow the execution of their offices, onely as a Trade with vnconſcionable <hi>thirſt</hi> of gaine vnto themſelues, more then with deſire to aduance the common good of the <hi>Church.</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>itia mater eſt omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum, &amp; maxime cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in animis non priua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum ſed magiſtratuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> innaſcatur. Iuſtin No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ell. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt. 8</note> And nothing doth more dazell the eye of Iudgement, or vnſtrengthen the band of dutie, then <hi>couetouſneſſe:</hi> ſpecially when ſhe is ſoueraigne <hi>commaundreſſe</hi> in the minds of ſuch <hi>ordinarie Maieſtrates.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:14815:17"/>
               <p>\ 2 Or, they thinke theſe <hi>Cannons</hi> and <hi>Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> (the due obſeruation whereof is committed to <note place="margin">Subdito fat non eſt lege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iniquitatis proſtringe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. Vlpian.</note> their truſt) are not good. And to accuſe the lawes of that iniquitie which could neuer as yet be iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by any their contumelious inuectiues, is a defect vnbeſeeming their <hi>Authoritie,</hi> whether we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider their places in <hi>relation</hi> to higher powers, whoſe hands they are, and therefore with vnited hearts ſhould ſet forward the execution of orders preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed: Or in reference to others whom Lawe hath confined within the borders of their iuriſdiction, amongſt whom they ſhould be fathers and fauters of <hi>vnitie</hi> and <hi>order.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. Or themſelues are <hi>Puritans</hi> in heart, and then they ride the roade waye of <hi>Athiſme,</hi> in kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping thoſe their dignities, Roomes and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſo much contrarie to their <hi>puritanized</hi> opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
               <p>4. Or they conceaue it skilleth not of what ſort their religion be, or with what different varietie they performe thoſe religious duties which in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and conſcience they owe to God-ward; And yet the very <hi>Turkes</hi> keepe themſelues in one and <note place="margin">Azor. 26.</note> the ſame inuiolable <hi>vniformity</hi> of ſeruice to that one God whom they acknowledge not, permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <note place="margin">Azor. 47.</note> any diſhonourable alteration. Becauſe they knowe that to ſwarue in the leaſt points which they <note place="margin">Azor. 13.</note> are perſwaded to be true, is errour in it ſelfe and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie to God.</p>
               <p>5. Or it may be <hi>Iuſtice</hi> concealed, or <hi>vniuſtice</hi> vnſeene, is all one, or of ſmall difference with
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14815:18"/> them God forbid ſuch an opinion ſhould euer enter a mans vnderſtanding, who hath the <hi>honour</hi> to beare the name of a Diuine, or Lawier. If that were true, a man need not to keepe in rule and order the <hi>operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of his ſoule, which is the true ſeate of <hi>vertue,</hi> but <note n="a" place="margin">Iudex non poteſt mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare pena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a lege ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. l. final. ne ſanctum bapt. itere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> onely endeauour to be iuſt ſo farre forth as it may come to the <hi>knowledge</hi> of men, and from ſuch no good ſeruice may be drawne or good expected. <hi>For where Impietie is Iuſtice in the ruler, all kindes of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries are open to the inferiour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Legiſlator minimas dunt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xit mulctas Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicibus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittat. Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. l. 9. de. l. ne in rebus maioribus arbitrio proprio Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantur, &amp; le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiores ſe eſte arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trentur. Martia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ad Turpilianu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> 6 Or they ſuppoſe their authoritie inueſted with <hi>Power</hi> to pardon, where the <hi>Law</hi> doth puniſh; if their ſuppoſall runne vpon thoſe <hi>penalties,</hi> which the <hi>Lawe</hi> hath left attributary to their diſcretion, the ſuppoſition is allowed. The leaſt amercements, fines and penalties are left to them, (ſmall things in the eye of the <hi>Lawe,</hi> are as nothing) And thoſe not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, leaſt any man ſhould ſeeme wiſer then the <hi>Lawe,</hi> and through <hi>libertie</hi> in ſmall things, abuſe his will in matters of greater moment. But where the <hi>Lawes</hi> with ſpeciall words haue entailed a <hi>puniſhment</hi> vpon the fact committed againſt their rule, they cannot without ſinne remit or diſpence in it. The Lawes are aboue them as they are aboue others, and muſt be <hi>Lords</hi> of men, not men <hi>Lord,</hi> of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Leges ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non homines le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos eſſe op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ortet. Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanius apud Plut.</note> Your actions (my maiſters of the faction) may coulourablie giue our <hi>Rulers</hi> the imputation of ſuch partiall and vnapprouable <hi>gouernment,</hi> but howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer you ſtroake and ſmooth your followers with comfort of your pretended intereſt. In thoſe rulers no man charitably minded wil ſuppoſe ſuch <hi>deiection</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:14815:18"/> of minde in men ſo graue, ſo learned, as to gleane in your fields what ſhould releeue them, or learne in your <hi>Schooles</hi> that which may direct them.</p>
               <p>I looke more to the inſight of their iudgment, which cannot but ſee their owne fall in your riſing, their ebbe in your flowe, their weakeneſſe in your ſtrength, their no-being when you are: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſithence <hi>Silence</hi> argues conſent; and ſufferance of errour, giues demonſtration of errour, in them that ſuffer it: If I were worthy to counſell them, (who are ſo wiſe in all the counſels of the Lawe) they ſhould, firſt, with-draw the vayle wherewith you doe labour to couer the Lawe. <note n="a" place="margin">Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſentire eſt facere cum poſſis arquere. Gloſsa. ad Rom. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>He which ſmoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth the light of the Lawe from others, doth Ecclipſe the light of conſcience in himſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Qui alios ab errore no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reuocat, ſeipſum er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat. Cap. qui alios de Haereticis.</note> Secondly, ſee and procure ſo much as in them ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all and euery <hi>Cannons and orders</hi> of the Church to be in all points duly obſerued. <hi>He who in the extent of his Gouernment, neglects the obſeruation of that which the Lawe councells, his endeuours haue their iſſue in vncurable inconueniences.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Boni ipſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conatus in exitus imedicabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les de ſinu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Ioſeph. in proemio antiq. Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daicarum,</note> Thirdly, not ſpare to execute the <hi>penalties</hi> in them ſeuerally mentioned vpon any that ſhall wittingly or wilfully breake or neglect to obſerue them. <hi>The execution of the Lawe is the life of the Lawe, and when the lawe of publicke conſtitution hath loſt his place, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate fancie will breed diſturbance of peace in euery place.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, not meaſure the <hi>validitie</hi> of ordinances by the ſleight conceipt which you haue of things commaunded, but by the common good, for which
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14815:19"/> they are propounded and publiſhed. <hi>Vpon the head of the Lawe all ſpecialties of common good are depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent:</hi> He which remembreth this, cannot but hate <note place="margin">Opportet odiſſe illos qui ſcribu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t decreta co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra leges. Eſchin. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Cleſiph.</note> them whoſe <hi>pennes are ready</hi> to write decrees a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lawes, and with all induſtrie endeauour ſo to draw the <hi>Circumference</hi> of his gouerment, that euery line of the <hi>Lawe</hi> may haue his <hi>vnion</hi> in the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of <hi>obedience</hi> to the ſettlement of common good.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>§: 9.</head>
               <p>For my laſt counſell, they are beholding vnto you, whoſe thoughts floating vp and downe the faddomleſſe bottome of your vnſteddy conceipts, haue (according to the <hi>modell)</hi> enſtamped the <hi>Croſse,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Learned diſc. pa. 122</note> the <hi>Fonte,</hi> and the <hi>Surpleſſe,</hi> with the note of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles. The more wantons haue you beene, and the worſe is your <hi>example</hi> ſo ſtubbornlie for trifles <hi>(as you terme them)</hi> to occaſion the contempt of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie,</hi> and to raiſe ſuch vnexcuſable hote conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions <note place="margin">Learn. diſc. pa. 75.</note> for trifles.</p>
               <p>The quiet repoſe of the Church (to which you ought to liue, rather then vnto your ſelues) requireth you: Firſt to accuſtome your <hi>mindes</hi> euen in trifles to regarde the authoritie of Lawes; <hi>The long per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted contempt of leſſer things doth giue heart of bould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the contempt of greater.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, to compoſe your labours in <hi>ſubiection</hi> to his rule, by whoſe <hi>ſupreame authoritie</hi> they are commaunded, and vpon whoſe fauour next vnder God the flouriſhing eſtate of the <hi>Church and Goſpell</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:14815:19"/> 
                  <hi>of Ieſus Chriſt</hi> hath his dependencie. Know you not <note place="margin">Obedientia eſt praetioſa &amp; praecla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſſima regu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> veneranda corona: ſine qua no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> veri reges ſed vt priuati eru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buntur ſine corona. Feretius de re militari. pa 88.</note> that the honour of the <hi>King</hi> conſiſteth in the loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all hearts of his people, that their true <hi>obedience,</hi> is his Crowne and dignitie, then can you not but knowe, he that hindreth or denyeth <hi>obedience,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſheth the dignitie of his crowne: A vice which no good heart can ſo much as conceiue without horrour.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Lear. diſc. pa. 76.</note> A <hi>Schoolemaiſter</hi> of yours hath ſaid: It is the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of a true <hi>Paſtor,</hi> to obſerue thoſe things which are commaunded by the lawfull Authoritie of the <hi>Church,</hi> concerning <hi>ceremoniall</hi> matters for order, and comlineſſe ſake and edification: and not to controule publicke Authoritie by his priuate iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. If you would frame and modell your ſelues by aſſaye of action ſutable vnto this leſſon, your <hi>obedience</hi> to the holy <hi>ordinances</hi> of the Church, would giue vs a ſound teſtimonie of your honour to the <hi>ſacred</hi> worde, by whoſe ſpeciall warrant her lawes doe exact your obedience. But herein you haue not as yet infeoffed your ſelues. Therefore if I ſhall pourtray the ſubſtance of the diſcourſers iudgement, and ſet it forth by thoſe coulours vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which you haue quartered your ſelues, You muſt eyther by your diſobedience conclude, that the Authoritie of this <hi>Church</hi> is vnlawfull, or by your inuectiues againſt the authorized <hi>ordinances</hi> of this Church, exclude your ſelues from the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of true <hi>Paſtors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take which you will, the choyſe is yours.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14815:20"/> Vpon the firſt I thinke you will not aduenture; and the ſecond, is too much vnpleaſing vnto your expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, yet worthily caſt vpon you, by that good ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which directeth your fierie toungs in the heate of your zeale <hi>ſcandalouſly</hi> to inueigh, and <hi>mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>partly</hi> to controule the <hi>State</hi> of this Church ſo happily eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, onely therefore becauſe it concurreth not in opinion and ſentence with you.</p>
               <p>You controule the <hi>Government,</hi> and cenſure it to <note place="margin">Admo. pa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5. Hay any. pa 13.</note> be <hi>Antichriſtian:</hi> You controule the <hi>State,</hi> and charge it with maiming and deforming the body of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You controule the <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>Princes,</hi> and call <note place="margin">Gilb. to Engl. &amp; Scotl. pa 5. 9. 11.</note> them <hi>trayters, deſtroyers</hi> of their ſpirituall Fathers, <hi>Conſumers</hi> of their country. Rebellious children.</p>
               <p>You controule the <hi>Lords</hi> of the moſt <hi>honourable priuie Counſell,</hi> and accuſe them of violent oppreſſion <note place="margin">Epiſ. from Scotland before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form. no enimy. pa. 3. 4.</note> of Gods <hi>Saints.</hi> Yea you bragge, that you dare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troule them, becauſe you know of no power but from aboue, and their power as all their force is bent (you ſay) to bereaue <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> of his gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>You controule the <hi>Lawes,</hi> and iudge them to be <note place="margin">Fen. atque Bridges. pa. 5. Suppl. pa. 95.</note> 
                  <hi>Sanctuaries</hi> of all wickedneſſe in this oppoſition againſt you. You controule the <hi>Iudges,</hi> and blame them as ſuffering <hi>impietie,</hi> to beare ſway againſt the <hi>maieſtie</hi> of God.</p>
               <p>You controule the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and condemne it <note place="margin">2. Admo. pa. 3.</note> as a <hi>Court</hi> where all honeſt men ſhall finde lacke of <hi>equitie.</hi> You controule the <hi>Conuocation houſe</hi> as a <note place="margin">Throgin. dia. 4.</note> houſe of <hi>Deuils,</hi> and account the <hi>Cleargie</hi> there aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, intollerable <hi>oppugners</hi> of Gods glory.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:14815:20"/>
               <p>\ You controule <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and call them <hi>incarnate</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Hay any. 28 Vdal. dial. 1</note> 
                  <hi>deuils; baſtardly gouernours; enemies to God; the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of Antichriſt;</hi> the <hi>plague</hi> of the <hi>Church:</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port <note place="margin">Cartvv. 2. repl. pa. 414</note> the beſt of them to be leſſe honeſt, then the worſt <hi>Puritane.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You controule the <hi>Miniſtrie,</hi> and denie it to be <note place="margin">Admo pa. 2. 4.</note> a right <hi>miniſtrie</hi> of God; The miniſters for the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter number, you terme <hi>ignorant Aſſes; filthy Swine;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Preface to the Deni.</note> 
                  <hi>Popiſh Prieſts, haulting Neutrals, Forlorne Atheiſts:</hi> amongſt whom (when your <hi>ſpirite</hi> is Searcher) no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <note place="margin">Gllby. pa. 20. 3. 30. 53. 89. Epiſt Fr. Scot. before reform. no enimy. &amp;c.</note> elſe is to be found, but <hi>a troope of bloudy-ſoule murtherers, and ſacrilegious Church-robbers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You controule the whole <hi>Commons</hi> and <hi>Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants</hi> of this <hi>Realme,</hi> (who directed by the Churches publicke order, doe make reuerent eſleeme of aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>obſeruances,</hi> according to the <hi>religion</hi> now eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed) <note place="margin">1. 2. admo.</note> And ſentence not onely them, but thoſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <note place="margin">Danger. poſit. l. 2.</note> which goe vnto their Churches for <hi>Infidels.</hi> By which meanes you make the <hi>Catholicks</hi> to bavvke our Churches.</p>
               <p>There was neuer any <hi>State</hi> more <hi>Turckiſhly</hi> hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <note place="margin">Surv. pa. 56</note> by vnchriſtian <hi>calumniations,</hi> then this <hi>State</hi> hath beene, and yet is, by diuers of you our <hi>Geneuating paſſauantians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For whereas the <hi>King</hi> in his <hi>princely</hi> perſwaſion of that profitable vſe, which the whole Church of this <hi>Kingdome</hi> may haue in the due obſeruation of the <hi>Cannons</hi> and <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> agreed vpon, hath by his <hi>Royall</hi> commaund, commended them vnto our practiſe. There are of you, and is one ſpeciall <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factioner</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rector ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claeſie Ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undunenſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> amongſt you, who daily exclaimeth againſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14815:21"/> them as <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Superſtitious,</hi> diſclaimeth their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, as <hi>ſinfull</hi> and <hi>damnable:</hi> and as if he would ſtrike vp the <hi>Drumme</hi> vnto <hi>Sedition,</hi> doth vnder a high commanding forme, <hi>adiure</hi> and charge his people to ioyne and holde with him: what ſhould make him ſo much to forget his dutie to the <hi>King,</hi> humilitie to the <hi>Church,</hi> charitie to his <hi>neighbours,</hi> and mercie which he oweth to <hi>himſelfe,</hi> his <hi>wife,</hi> and his <hi>children?</hi> I will not now examine: but if he had kept his <hi>orderleſſe</hi> opinions priuate, and not made them the common ſubiects of <hi>publicke diſcourſes,</hi> to frame in the harts of his hearers a diſlike of the <hi>ſtate</hi> preſent, and fancie of his <hi>faction;</hi> it would haue beene (in my poore opinion) though no way appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uable yet more pardonable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>§: 10</head>
               <p>Such contumelious <hi>maledictions</hi> (you the <hi>Maiors</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> of his <hi>Highneſſe Citties</hi> and <hi>Townes corporate)</hi> doe heare many. What may hinder that you will not, or doth <hi>affright</hi> you that you dare not, but make approbation of euery both <hi>ſpeach</hi> and <hi>action,</hi> whereof they giue you euidence; is beſt knowne within your ſelues, where no eyes doe ſhine but yours.</p>
               <p>Your <hi>authoritie</hi> to ſee the Lawes of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip <note place="margin">Cartw. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eply.</note> duly executed, and <hi>orders</hi> of the Church reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently obſerued, hath the cleare light of generall acknowledgment. And if it were ſo freely perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14815:21"/> by you, as it is fully permitted to you, theſe <hi>ill-languaged Nouelliſts</hi> could not haue gotten ſuch gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell audience in your publicke aſſemblies, nor diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Conſtitutions</hi> ſo much tain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the reputation of your <hi>Cittizens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It muſt not be denied you, that our Fathers ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer had any <hi>ſocietie</hi> ſo warrantable for inſtitution, or wiſe for <hi>gouerment,</hi> that could retaine all her parts in due <hi>obedience.</hi> Mans will is by <hi>Nature</hi> auerſe from all <hi>obedience</hi> to the ſacred Lawes of his <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and in the deprauation of his minde, would imploye all both <hi>witte</hi> and <hi>valour,</hi> to the extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of euill, had not that wiſdome which <hi>ordaineth</hi> order and regiment obſeruable in pollitique affaires, by Lawes prouided to frame our outward actions to that common good, for which <hi>ſocieties</hi> were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained.</p>
               <p>Theſe Lawes are like ſo many inſtructiue <hi>Bridles</hi> to reſtraine the head-long courſe of <hi>ſelfe-will,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in loue with her owne councels, and to guide it in the way which Iudgment with conſent hath approued: The <hi>Raynes</hi> are in your hands, and had you euenly borne them, <hi>Newfangliſme</hi> in going backward from the <hi>State,</hi> could not haue gotten ſo farre forward in <hi>oppoſition</hi> to the <hi>State.</hi> But too much, or too little, as too ſoone, or too late, hath alwayes beene dangerous in <hi>gouerment,</hi> and your <hi>ill-carriage</hi> hath giuen ſome opportunitie to winne head of you, whom otherwiſe you might haue brought and kept in an vniformitie of <hi>Raine.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:14815:22"/>
               <p>\ To attribute this <hi>defect</hi> vnto your vnskilfulneſſe in the <hi>mannage</hi> of publicke occurrents, it is a <hi>diſgrace</hi> I would no way giue to the ſimpleſt. Vertuous men doe oftentimes erre, and you may faile in this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, not becauſe you would, but for that it is of more harde <hi>digeſtion,</hi> then your vertue can well ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Sleights</hi> of this <hi>Schiſme</hi> are cunning, the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes</hi> ſubtle, the <hi>panges</hi> vehement, the <hi>affections</hi> ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, the <hi>paſsions</hi> vnrulie, and <hi>attempts</hi> impetuous, with contempt of your <hi>magiſtracie,</hi> and <hi>deſpight</hi> to the lawfull ordination of our <hi>Cleargie:</hi> All which are ſo <hi>palliated</hi> with a ſeeming grauitie in their <hi>beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour,</hi> and puritie of <hi>Goſpell</hi> in their <hi>mouthes,</hi> that to the tryall of it, there appertaineth a great deale more then ordinarie conceipt can reach vnto.</p>
               <p>The greater cauſe haue you ( ) for ſeeking your owne aduiſe in theſe things, to cleaue vnto the <hi>Councells</hi> of thoſe reuerend <hi>Prelates,</hi> to whom the reſolutions of doubts in theſe cauſes, is by the Lawe of God and man referred, as in other cauſes you would to the reuerend <hi>Iudges,</hi> thoſe <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> of the land.</p>
               <p>And to attend the commaund of the <hi>ſupreame Commaunder,</hi> whoſe <hi>ſoueraigntie</hi> muſt giue you war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for the order in doing all things, not onely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propiate to your <hi>Corporations,</hi> but alſo pertinent to the practiſe of <hi>religion,</hi> the due reuerence whereof, bringeth with it the happy <hi>continuance</hi> of euery com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weale.</p>
               <p>And ſith his Iudgement, by whom all other inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14815:22"/> iudgements in <hi>congruitie</hi> of reaſon are to be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled, hath propounded this order of <hi>diuine ſeruice,</hi> to be equally kept, by all his louing ſubiects of this <hi>kingdome,</hi> let it not greeue you, (as you reioyce to <note place="margin">Zonaras in Valentinia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> ſee him ſit in the <hi>throane,)</hi> to beare a little part with him in the <hi>burthen,</hi> and within your <hi>precincts</hi> to ſee that regardfully performed, which he hath roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally eſtabliſhed.</p>
               <p>You are the <hi>Deputies</hi> of <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> and did you but remember this? you would not ſuffer ſuch impudent <hi>contempt</hi> of Church gouernment, ſo directly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded by the moſt <hi>mature diſcretion</hi> of his royall decrees.</p>
               <p>You would not giue <hi>tolleration</hi> to them, who eſteeme ſecret <hi>Corners</hi> and priuate <hi>Conuenticles,</hi> (the <hi>Schooles of maledictions</hi> againſt <hi>princes and rulers)</hi> to be of equall vſe, with holy Churches, for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke performance of <hi>diuine ſeruice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You would not be ſilent, when thoſe holy <hi>Hymnes, Venite exultemus, Te Deum laudamus, Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictus,</hi> are put to ſilence in your publicke aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies.</p>
               <p>You would not permit (that peculiar <hi>Hymne</hi> of Chriſtianitie) the bleſſed <hi>Virgins Magnificat,</hi> to be ſerued with a <hi>writ of eiectment</hi> out of your Churches.</p>
               <p>You would not ſee your people (whoſe <hi>Elders, Auncients,</hi> and <hi>Maiors</hi> you are) to want their weekely <hi>Sacrifices</hi> of Prayer to God offered in the <hi>ſacred Liturgies</hi> for the appeaſing of Gods wrath, and auerting of publicke euills due to our publicke ſinnes.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:14815:23"/>
               <p>\ You would not allowe the <hi>omiſsion,</hi> but indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour the continued <hi>publication</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtolicall, Athenaſian</hi> and <hi>Niſen Creed,</hi> thoſe treaſures of ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable price to ſo many as haue not giuen vp the <hi>ghoſt</hi> of beleefe.</p>
               <p>You would not giue leaue to <hi>pare</hi> away from the ſeruice of God that <hi>Hymne of glory</hi> (then which) nothing doth ſound more <hi>heauenly</hi> in the eares of mortall men, nor more witneſſe our <hi>honour</hi> to the holy <hi>Trinitie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You would not ſuffer your <hi>Miniſters</hi> at their owne <hi>pleaſures</hi> to alter and change, to vſe or not to vſe that order of <hi>Common prayer</hi> to God, which diuine wiſdome hath agreed on, and <note n="a" place="margin">Permitte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> debes aliquid fieri contra no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtras prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptiones occaſione religionis. Iuſt. rectori prouinciaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Nouell. 17.</note> ſoueraigne <hi>authoritie</hi> commanded to be vſed; but as farre forth as you may, prouide that his <hi>Princely</hi> commaund bee not fruſtrated by the vndutifull diſpoſition of any.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If any ſhall offend againſt the Lawe, whether he be</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Lear. diſc. pa. 141.</note> 
                  <hi>Preacher or hearer, beſide the Eccleſiaſticall Cenſure which he ſhould not eſcape, he is alſo to be puniſhed in body by the Ciuill Magiſtrate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is their owne <hi>rule,</hi> whoſe vntulineſſe your hand doth ſo much ſpare, and in fauour of whom you keepe your vnder-ſworde of <hi>Iuſtice</hi> ſo ſtiflye ſheathed, that neither the zeale which you owe to the <hi>Church,</hi> nor regarde of <hi>Soueraignes</hi> iuſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund can vnſcaberd it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faction</hi> and priuate <hi>reſpects,</hi> doe not become <hi>Magiſtrates:</hi> but if you will make a <hi>partie?</hi> the <note place="margin">Partialitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ciuitate</note>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:14815:23"/> Lawe doth ſhew you what ſide to followe: And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <note place="margin">eſſe tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>men in Caſeo, dixit Baldus. ad. l. vinc. de cadu tolle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</note> you be <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> hath appointed you a <hi>maiſter,</hi> whom you are to obay. <hi>Dutie</hi> both in you and your <hi>Miniſters,</hi> ought to be relatiue vnto that which <hi>Kingly authoritie</hi> doth by lawe preſcribe, eſpecially when <hi>reaſon</hi> doth not enforce, that the lawe of <hi>reaſon</hi> or of God doth enioyne the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie.</p>
               <p>The more vnreaſonable are thoſe your <hi>Pariſh</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom 13. omnis ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. &amp;c. hoc quoad ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualia ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet vim praecepti, Ferdma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dus Vaſquius contr. verſ. ill. l. 1. pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſat. numer. 125.</note> 
                  <hi>Biſhops</hi> which doe ſo vndutifully reiect what is commanded, and contentiouſlie ſeeke the <hi>innoua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>order</hi> eſtabliſhed, without warrant of that <hi>ground</hi> wherevpon the change muſt growe, ſuch <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſideration</hi> cannot bee well borne within them, whom <hi>learning</hi> hath enabled much more ſoundly to diſcerne of theſe differences, if <hi>parcialitie</hi> did not tranſport their reſolutions beyond the rule of <hi>iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You neuer ſawe a good <hi>Scholler</hi> arrogant, for <note place="margin">Vbi eſt in columitas obedientia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ibi eſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ſanae doctrinae. Leo mag. epiſ. 87.</note> the more he knowes, the more of his <hi>weakneſse</hi> he vnderſtands. <hi>Youth</hi> and <hi>Ignorance</hi> are the <hi>Fountes</hi> of <hi>Shiſme.</hi> The leaſt <hi>knowledge</hi> is euer moſt proud. This in ſome of your conceipts, deiects reuerend fathers; And to your better liking, blowes vpp waitleſſe youthes, to preach inſolently to your abuſed <hi>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance,</hi> who flatter your prepoſterous zeale, <hi>ſinke your treaſure,</hi> vndoe your corporations, decaye your trades, impoueriſh your <hi>cittizens,</hi> ſeduce your <hi>chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> miſſead your <hi>ſeruants,</hi> and make religion their ſtalking horſe, vnder whoſe bellie they ſhoote at what their <hi>appettites</hi> doe moſt affect.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:14815:24"/>
               <p>\ Many of you do ſet a higher price on your know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in <hi>Diuinitie,</hi> then any reaſonable creature will giue you for it. Will it pleaſe you to looke to the times of olde, before <hi>Newfangliſme</hi> began to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe reſiance within your walles? you ſhall finde, that vnneceſſary <hi>ſwaruing</hi> from the Practiſe of the <hi>Church,</hi> did neuer yeeld experience of good vnto your citties.</p>
               <p>Conſider the tyme preſent, wherein your <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueliſts</hi> doe weigh the rules of religion in a popular ballance, which the world knowes will be carried awaye with very ſlender circumſtances.) And ſaye I praye you, what other maye be the drift of theſe <hi>diuiſions</hi> and <hi>ſubdiuiſions,</hi> wherewith they of the fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion doe teare and turmoile the <hi>State</hi> and <hi>gouerment,</hi> but to faſhion your mindes with diſcontentment to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>State:</hi> and why towards the <hi>State?</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth that when the cloude of <hi>preiudice,</hi> and miſte of paſſionate <hi>affections,</hi> hath darkened the light of your iudgement, they may bring in another kinde of regiment, and laye a <hi>Yoake</hi> vpon your ſhoulders, which your Fathers did neuer beare. Miſfaſhioned preconceipts, are eaſilie ledde with any ſleight <hi>decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> of ſpecialties, which may giue <hi>enducements</hi> to the conceipt.</p>
               <p>For this cauſe they would perſwade you to leaue this diſordered ſtate of ours (ſo their <hi>charitie</hi> doth <note place="margin">Lear. diſc. pa. 8.</note> terme it) and with vndeniable earneſtneſſe doe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune <note place="margin">Omnia no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua pulchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine ſunt decorata.</note> you, to giue <hi>intertainment</hi> to that moſt beautifull (as their fancie doth conceiue) order of <hi>eccleſiaſticall regiment,</hi> which God ſo manifeſtly doth
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14815:24"/> bleſſe and proſper in our <hi>neighbours</hi> hands.</p>
               <p>This is that which induceth both ſome of you, and many the <hi>common</hi> deceiued multitude, to looke a <hi>ſquinte</hi> at the <hi>ſtate</hi> of the Church wherein they liue, and in erecting the <hi>fabricke</hi> of their <hi>reformation,</hi> to caſt their eyes vpon the patterne at <hi>Geneua.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is out-landiſh faſhion ſo <hi>faſhionable</hi> to your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, that for concurrencie with them you will be <hi>diſalegianced</hi> vnto his <hi>Maieſtie?</hi> it ſhall not be in my thought, that any true harted <hi>Brittaine</hi> can ſo farre <hi>baſtardize</hi> his naturall affection, that forraine coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell ſhould be of more <hi>moment,</hi> to worke and frame in him, the ſtampe and <hi>character</hi> of a ſtrange <hi>pollicie,</hi> then the commaund of a moſt iuſt <hi>King,</hi> to keepe him in an order of <hi>vniformitie,</hi> ſo well beſeeming the Church and conformable to the <hi>gouerment</hi> of our countrie.</p>
               <p>I could in due <hi>moderation</hi> pleade in <hi>barre</hi> againſt you: the practiſe of ſuch <hi>reformaliſts</hi> in ſome other place, where experience hath found, and <hi>Authoritie</hi> proclaimed the <hi>method</hi> of Church <hi>regiment,</hi> which they ſo earneſtly queſt for, to be vnſound in <hi>diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Proclam. Scot. 1582.</note> derogatorie to <hi>Princely</hi> rule, and onely maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by complots of ſeditious execution: ſo vnbleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed hath it beene in our neighbours hands, but I loue not to <hi>blaunch</hi> thoſe actions.</p>
               <p>If the <hi>graces</hi> wherewith the God of all grace hath enriched this <hi>State,</hi> were ſo gracefull with vs, as <hi>nature</hi> willeth, becauſe we are <hi>Brittaines,</hi> and grace requireth, becauſe we are <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> they would not ſuffer the <hi>glory</hi> of their owne Church, which by
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14815:25"/> an <hi>incomparable</hi> diſtance, doth out-ſhine the others in <hi>excellencie,</hi> to be ſo diſparaged, but as children which complie with ther mother in all Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, exhibite themſelues <hi>inſtruments</hi> to imbrace that forme of <hi>Religion,</hi> which God as a ſtrong eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, to be moſt pleaſing vnto him, and profitable for vs, hath ſealed with ſo great bleſſings of <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>proſperitie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The effects, men ſay doe beare <hi>reſemblances</hi> of their cauſes, and if the richeſt effects doe inferre the <hi>nobleſt</hi> faculties, you may bouldly giue this <hi>pollicie</hi> your letters <hi>teſtimoniall,</hi> vnder the ſeales of your <hi>Citties</hi> and <hi>Incorporations</hi> to be the beſt pollicie, for this gouerment to obſerue, becauſe vnder this it doth beſt maintaine it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Therefore as you tender the <hi>peace</hi> of the Church, the <hi>quiet</hi> of the Countrie, and ſeruice both of <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>King:</hi> If there be in you that fatherly care of the common good, which hath euer beene the <hi>crowne and glorie</hi> of a Chriſtian <hi>Maiorate,</hi> reforme your owne former miſſead opinions: <hi>You are the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond lights of the Common-wealth, and when the eye is dimme the body is darke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conforme your religious exerciſes to that forme <note place="margin">Conſulte agit qui praecepto legis obte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perat. ca. de furtis. l. in ciuilem.</note> which the Lawe alloweth, it is an inſeperable <hi>inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> vnto gouerment, that the Magiſtrates to whom the charge of the <hi>Lawe</hi> is committed be principall <hi>Obſeruators</hi> of the Lawe themſelues; their example muſt be a <hi>Lanterne</hi> of direction vnto the reſt, for they ſhall finde it moſt certaine; <hi>When the Rulers doe runne at randome, the people will beare no byas.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:14815:25"/>
               <p>\ Abandon from you the maiſters of <hi>noueltie</hi> and workers of <hi>innouation,</hi> what apparance ſoeuer there be in the <hi>noueltie,</hi> you are ſure to looſe by the <hi>bargaine,</hi> the vtilitie cannot be ſo helpfull, but the <hi>noueltie</hi> would bee more hurtfull. For if it ſhould be lawfull for euery man to caſt the frame of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in the <hi>mould</hi> of their owne fancies, The <hi>ſcruples</hi> and <hi>inconueniences</hi> would be no leſſe in the Church, then the ſuites at the common-lawe, in number infinite, if euery man had power to create a <hi>newfound</hi> eſtate <hi>intaile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that they may bee the better acquainted with your conſtant <hi>reſolution:</hi> tell your <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> it is not lawfull for them to varye in their <hi>habites, manners,</hi> and <hi>orders,</hi> who ſhould bee <hi>Preſidents</hi> vnto other men of the beautye of order.</p>
               <p>Tell your deceaued <hi>Cittizens,</hi> there is not a <note place="margin">Qui ſub ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine ſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit eſſe, non Iuuetur eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legijs &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficijs qui ſubijciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur. Paſchalis Secundus.</note> more apparant marke of <hi>loyaltie</hi> then <hi>Obedience,</hi> or neceſſary for the <hi>manutention</hi> of Pollicie: <hi>And he that hath no conſcience to obey his Soueraigne, cannot with conſcience chalenge the benefit of a Subiect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tell the <hi>factious</hi> their humour is good for nothing but to breed <hi>muddy Ecles,</hi> which muſt be ratled out with a <hi>thunder.</hi> And though their contentions be pleaſing to the common aduerſarie of our <hi>ſoules,</hi> who delighteth with diſcord amongſt <hi>familiars,</hi> yet it is moſt vnpleaſfull to God, whoſe ſeruants are beſt knowne by the <hi>Character</hi> of loue.</p>
               <p>I know their diſordered <hi>humors</hi> will much ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke at <hi>contradiction,</hi> and ſtorme againſt you,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14815:26"/> when you would reforme them; but when you ſhall reproue their ſuch <hi>humours,</hi> by the <hi>Oracles</hi> of <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> which haue no ſide reſpect vnto perſons, they will with more reaſon brooke the reproofe, and readily yeeld their <hi>obedience.</hi> For this cauſe it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooueth you, to haue a true eye vnto the lawes of this gouerment, and giue no paſſage vnto fancie, which ſhall preſume to appoſe againſt them.</p>
               <p>To <hi>calumniate</hi> and <hi>impunge</hi> the lawes of the Church, was alwayes deemed an <hi>exorbitant</hi> offence, and he that can, but will not, ſet a <hi>pegge</hi> in their <hi>wheele</hi> to ſtay it, is by his <hi>ſufferance,</hi> Actor with them in the the euill that ariſeth from it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>§. 11.</head>
               <p>Your ſuch offences you excuſe with the <hi>plea</hi> of conſcience. There is nothing more common then to heare and meete with paſſages of diſloialtie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretext of <hi>conſcience,</hi> vpon ſuppoſed offence whereof, there is ſuch ſtraying of <hi>Gnats,</hi> ſuch ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of <hi>Cammels,</hi> ſuch ſtumbling at <hi>Strawes,</hi> ſuch leaping ouer <hi>Blockes,</hi> ſuch acquiting for the <hi>Horſe,</hi> ſuch hanging for the <hi>Saddle,</hi> ſuch excuſing for the <hi>Sword,</hi> and accuſing for the <hi>Scabberd,</hi> as in conſcience was neuer ſeene.</p>
               <p>I will not preſume to cenſure your <hi>conſciences,</hi> in this refuſall of <hi>orders</hi> preſcribed, which you ſuppoſe warranted with the pretence of <hi>conſcience;</hi> yet this I muſt tell you, if that you were men of ſuch exact and preciſe <hi>conſcience</hi> as you pretend and beare the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14815:26"/> world in hand, your <hi>conſcience</hi> ſhould not peruert and falſifie the leaſt circumſtance which doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>Diuines</hi> or other men of exquiſite <hi>conſcience;</hi> you would not ſo <hi>contenciouſlie</hi> hunt after the receipt of your owne conceipts, without eyther <hi>ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi> or <hi>conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience</hi> of the publicke good. You could not (without <hi>conſcience</hi> or <hi>charitie)</hi> ſo raſhly condemne whom you liſt, for whatſoeuer your <hi>fancie</hi> doth diſalowe, or ſo bouldly impute all corruption to the obiect of your diſlike, but with full conſent and conſcience would condeſcend vnto that, which the light of <hi>Nature,</hi> the Lawe of <hi>Scripture,</hi> and ſentence of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie</hi> hath offered, warranted and receaued.</p>
               <p>A good <hi>Conſcience</hi> is grounded vpon ſure know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but they which write in defence of your <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The author of the peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to her maieſtie. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, pag. 18.</note> are enforced to acknowledge <hi>that with whom the truth is, they knowe not.</hi> Therefore, by the iuſt <hi>ſearment</hi> of the higheſt wiſdome, your ſuch conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is eyther an ignorant <hi>fantaſie</hi> or an arrogant <hi>vanity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The holy <hi>Scripture</hi> is the aſſured ground, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to build <hi>conſcience:</hi> the infallible rule to direct conſcience, &amp; whereas it hath moſt inuincible <hi>autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie</hi> which ought by ſinguler <hi>praerogatiue</hi> to decide all doubts, any either <hi>Papiſt, Anabaptiſt,</hi> or <hi>Nouelliſt,</hi> can moue in theſe controuerſed cauſes, what <hi>argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">M Hooker. l. 1. pref. pa. 11.</note> haue your Leaders ſhewed you, whereby it was euer prooued that any one <hi>ſentence</hi> of <hi>ſcripture</hi> doth neceſſarily enforce thoſe things wherein you concurre with them againſt the orders of your owne <hi>Church?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:14815:27"/>
               <p>\ It is to be feared that you laye the ſafetie of your <hi>conſcience</hi> vpon the credit of your owne conceipts, or other mens humours. and that you ſquare your <hi>Conſcience</hi> by the rule of your cuſtome, which hath ſeized vpon, and ſo farre entangled you in this <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction,</hi> that you know not how to leaue the <hi>opinions</hi> you haue ſo much approued, and with <hi>conſcience</hi> (that is, your credit) to receaue the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances whereby your opinions are checked; this <hi>diſtraction</hi> of thoughts in you, is that <hi>alarnm</hi> which conſcience giues you.</p>
               <p>If you bee vnwilling to enter the doing of that which you haue formerly condemned, I maruaile not. The nature of man is not willing to condemne it ſelfe, but to deuiſe ſo many ſhifts of <hi>wittes inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> to auoide that which all <hi>iudicious</hi> learning doth approue; I greatly maruaile at in you, who deſire to be eſteemed the holy <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and learned <hi>Sages</hi> of this age: and therefore doe intreate you to looke into the <hi>Inuentarie</hi> of your conſcience, whether the painfull <hi>imaginations</hi> wherewith you are perplexed to forgoe that in which you ſo much delighted, be not that griefe of <hi>Conſcience</hi> ſo much pretended.</p>
               <p>As for the euill whereof the <hi>Church</hi> doth blame you; if you would <hi>conſcienciouſlie</hi> diſplaye it before your <hi>conſcience,</hi> I thinke in conſcience you would not ſo earneſtlie <hi>repugne</hi> at that Booke of <hi>Vnifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie,</hi> for which they whoſe ſpirits indeauored the labours of beſt excellencie, did expone themſelues to the triall of hardeſt <hi>difficulties.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:14815:27"/>
               <head>§. 12.</head>
               <p>It is diſordered (you ſay) and muſt it be altered by your owne priuate warrant? will nothing <hi>gaine</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. Admo. pa. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>eſteeme</hi> with you, ſauing what proceedeth from your owne deuiſe? The publicke iudgement of the <hi>Church</hi> doth approoue it, if the <hi>Lawes</hi> of publicke <hi>determination</hi> may not ouer-rule your priuate, <hi>though probable reſolutions,</hi> where is the poſſibilitie of ſociable life? where is the <hi>bonde</hi> of your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to morrall dutie? where is the power of the <hi>Church,</hi> to admitte or reiect, what ſhall be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie or inconuenient, for the ſafetie and ſecuritie of her <hi>ſocietie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it be lawfull for euery <hi>paſsionate</hi> ſpirit carried with an affectation of <hi>Noueltie,</hi> to <hi>repeale</hi> Lawes which Authoritie hath enacted, to breake <hi>cuſtomes</hi> which <hi>Antiquitie</hi> hath commended; to change <hi>Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> which <hi>Experience</hi> hath approued, to peruert <hi>order</hi> which Iudgement hath eſtabliſhed, and by ſuiting all occurrents to their priuate <hi>humors,</hi> to <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouate</hi> that forme of <hi>gouerment</hi> which this <hi>king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> hath happily followed, and <hi>heauen</hi> richly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? where is that ſo much valued wiſdome of the <hi>Auncient?</hi> where is the allowance which time gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to things profitablie honeſt? where is that <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premicie</hi> which God hath impropriate to the <hi>Scepter</hi> of <hi>Princes,</hi> as their peculiar right?</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:14815:28"/>
               <p>\ I heare you confeſſe it, take heede you be not found ſecretly to <hi>vndermine</hi> it, but if you be reall as you are verball in the recognition of his <hi>ſupreame Authoritie,</hi> forgoe the thoughts of your <hi>Conſiſtoriall gouerment,</hi> which affecteth the vſurpation of his <hi>Princely</hi> rule, and giue his religious Offices in the gouerment of the Church, their <hi>honourable</hi> iſſues, in your obedience, to that forme of <hi>Church gouerment,</hi> which he hath allowed, and eſpecially declared in that booke of <hi>Vniformitie;</hi> wherein if there had beene that apparant cauſe of <hi>reformation,</hi> as you pretended, we haue iuſt cauſe to ſay, it was more in his <hi>heart</hi> to haue done it, then in yours to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>§. 13.</head>
               <p>You implead the <hi>formes</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> as ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious, <note place="margin">Proclam. 5. Marti 1603 Procla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 16. Iulii. 1604. Epiſt. ad Lodouicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Borbonium principem.</note> and not <hi>Apoſtolicke,</hi> yet you heard them to bee iuſtified out of the practiſe of the <hi>primitiue Church.</hi> And <hi>Beza</hi> warranteth, you are not abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely bound to imitate the times, which haue beene in euery particuler, or without exception to receaue the <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> which the <hi>Church Apoſtolicke</hi> eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med as moſt profitable for their times. And ſeeing that thoſe graue learned men vpon whoſe <hi>iudgment</hi> you laide the <hi>Burthen,</hi> of vpholding your cauſe by <hi>argument,</hi> did in that <hi>committall</hi> conference, giue their conſent to the obſeruation of the rites in vſe, you ſhould haue preſently imbraced them, as free from all ſuppoſall of <hi>ſuperſtition.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:14815:28"/>
               <p>\ If we did ſo iuſtly deſerue to be touched with the note of <hi>ſuperſtition,</hi> as in this caſe you haue ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined we doe, I would rather humblie ſeeke and ſuppliantly begge pardon of my <hi>ſoules Sauiour,</hi> then meditate wordes of perſwaſion for your <hi>ſubmiſsion</hi> vnto this order.</p>
               <p>Wherein, thoſe vnſownder times, whereof you ſpeake haue done amiſſe, that comes not within the <hi>Circuite</hi> of my thoughts; but ſeeing this Church, whereof you are <hi>members</hi> (vnleſſe by pertinacie in <hi>Schiſme,</hi> you diſioynt your ſelues) hath required you to reuerence this order as holy, &amp; to obſerue it as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoouefull for the excerciſe of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> dutie: I do greatly wiſh that your mindes now poſſeſſed with <hi>diſlike,</hi> would not ſet them vp as your markes to ſhoote at, nor by way of <hi>Scorne</hi> to contradict what <hi>Authoritie</hi> hath ſeriouſlie commaunded, but with ready <hi>deſtination</hi> to receaue whatſoeuer is in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of <hi>Religion,</hi> according to the Lawes for that purpoſe now eſtabliſhed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>§. 14.</head>
               <p>Some of them, I thinke you could be contented with, but the <hi>Croſſe</hi> ſtands in your way, and I mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile not, your ſelues delight ſo much to ſtand in <note place="margin">Diſcourſe of the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles at Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ckford. pa. 54.</note> the <hi>Croſſe-way;</hi> yet did the Church by your owne confeſſion, for one thouſand and three hundred yeares, obſerue the <hi>Ceremonie</hi> of Croſſing, as an outward teſtimony of their inward faith, inſomuch <note place="margin">Baſil. de ſpu. ſancto. cap. 27.</note> that all which truſted in the name of the <hi>Lord Ieſu,</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:14815:29"/> were marked with the ſigne of the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> faith <hi>Saint Baſill,</hi> and whoſoeuer of you ſhall vſe the ſigne of <note place="margin">Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plea to an Apologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal. epiſt. Sect. 2. pa. 141.</note> the <hi>Croſse</hi> in this manner, I can aſſure you is farre from <hi>Popiſh ſuperſtition;</hi> if you will not beleeue me aske <hi>Maiſter Willet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I haue heard of a man whoſe mouth (like a <hi>Mill</hi> that cannot grinde but with foule water) doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ouer-runne with termes of <hi>obſcenitie</hi> againſt the approued cerimonies of holy Church, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumelie againſt men of honourable ſeruice, onelie therefore becauſe they runne not with him, in the ſame exceſſe of vnaduiſed zeale.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Ipſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vbi eum deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia ſuperbae impietatis irriſit in il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> qui in eu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> credere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t frontibus infixit, vbi eſt quoda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo ſedes verecundiae vt de nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne eius fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſcat: &amp; magis dei gloria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hominem diligat. Auguſt. in Euangel. tracta. 53. in fine. Baptiz. 16. Ianu. Anno Do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 1601. Tacitus l. 14 annal. Sepult. 20. Ia. 1601.</note> This fellow hearing a childe of his, at the time of <hi>Baptiſme</hi> to be ſigned, with the <hi>Croſſe</hi> in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, (the ſeate of honeſty) did ſo frettingly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine thereat, that in the heate of his newfangled ſpirit, he ſaid, it would haue done as much good, if it had beene done in the ſeate of natures impuritie. But what followed this prophane contempt of that <hi>ſignificatiue Ceremonie,</hi> and <hi>Character</hi> of Chriſtianitie? I know you deſire to heare, and but to ſatiſfie your deſire, as alſo to giue witneſſe to the cauſe in hand, I could contentiuely ſilence it, leaſt vnhappily any of you ſhould thinke me as <hi>Caius Caſsius</hi> ſpake of himſelfe in the <hi>Romaine Senate,</hi> carryed with too much loue of Auncient holy cuſtomes. His next borne Childe, being a goodly boye, wanted that place of <hi>Natures</hi> vent.</p>
               <p>Whether <hi>Nature</hi> were hindred in producing of her intended effect, by ſome Groſſe defection in the naturall cauſes, or elſe that the <hi>Author</hi> of Nature
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14815:29"/> (who according to the rules of true <hi>Philoſophie</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly concurreth with all ſingular, <hi>ſecundarie</hi> cauſes, euen to their perticular effects, for ends beſt knowne to his all-ſeeing prouidence, doth at any time with-draw his <hi>co-operatiue</hi> power: I recommend it to your conſultation, yet I doubt the tempeſt of your affections will beat againſt, what the hand of <hi>iudgment</hi> doth build.</p>
               <p>Many did admire it, as a <hi>blowe</hi> giuen by his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine hand, whoſe power ruleth all from the higheſt <hi>Seraphyn</hi> to the loweſt <hi>Syncphee;</hi> and in the duty of a Chriſtian, I wiſh the remembrance of it, might not onely water the Father with the liquor of <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> vnto order, that he may proſper, as a well roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Plant</hi> in the garden of <hi>Humilitie;</hi> but alſo induce his brother (who in the worke of his Miniſtery im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugneth this vſe of the croſſe) vnto a more dutifull conformity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>§. 15.</head>
               <p>Two things haue giuen great ſwaye vnto your <note place="margin">Qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiores ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to magis ſub praetex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu ſanctita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis nocent: Ambr. de Noc &amp; Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha. ca. 14.</note> ſect, the one is, <hi>apparancie</hi> of zeale, the other <hi>ſubtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> of diſcourſe (the glareing baites of masked follie) vailed with the ſhew of <hi>deuotion,</hi> ambitiouſly deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to be eſteemed, what you are not,) you haue miſlead poore beguiled <hi>Soules,</hi> to that they ſhould not, and with <hi>facillitie</hi> of ſpeach endeauoured to entangle the choiſeſt wittes in the toile of your <hi>miſconceipted</hi> opinions. For this cauſe: You <hi>Gentlemen</hi> at the <hi>Lawe,</hi> commonly haue your eyes
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14815:30"/> dazeled with the firſt view of <hi>Fancies</hi> proiects, your affections ſounded with the firſt touch of zeales <hi>paſsion;</hi> your eares tickled with the firſt note of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors tune, and your Chambers ſtored with the firſt <hi>fruites</hi> of their wittes <hi>follie,</hi> to the end <hi>(forſooth)</hi> that by your hands, they might more eaſilie ſpread abroad, and be diſperſed among the <hi>Brethren</hi> of the cauſe, whoſe foſter friends <hi>Noueltie</hi> might make you.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding the quickeſt wittes in <hi>pliancie</hi> of diſpoſition to <hi>Noueltie,</hi> doe eaſily giue fauour to <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell opinions,</hi> not as reaſon doth warrant, but as Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie doth conceaue them; yet I make no queſtion, that you my maiſters (the <hi>Gentlemen Apprentiſes</hi> at the Lawe) will ſo goe with the <hi>current</hi> and <hi>ſtreame</hi> of the lawe, that the <hi>King</hi> who is the life of the <hi>Law, the liuing Lawe,</hi> the <hi>Patron</hi> of your <hi>ſtudie,</hi> and <hi>founder</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Philo. l. 2. de vita moſis.</note> of your <hi>honour,</hi> ſhall not haue cauſe ſo much as to heare <hi>Complaint</hi> of your any further <hi>conniuence</hi> to <hi>enormities,</hi> or indulgence to <hi>factions,</hi> or ſupportance of <hi>diſcentious</hi> partialities.</p>
               <p>As <hi>Charles</hi> the fift of <hi>Fraunce</hi> ſayd of his <hi>Colledge</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Chopinus de do. Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. pa. 594.</note> of Lawyers in <hi>Angew;</hi> your Houſes of Innes of <hi>Court,</hi> are to his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> a fluent <hi>Spring,</hi> to furniſh him with men of high Councell, both for the good gouerment of themſelues, and procurement of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers good.</p>
               <p>Two things much commended in you, and much commended to you, that as you ſtudie the benefit of your <hi>Countrie</hi> by your ſtudy at the Lawe, your conformitie with the Lawe, may <hi>crowne</hi> your ſtudy
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14815:30"/> with <hi>wiſdome,</hi> your dayes with <hi>peace,</hi> your know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge with <hi>obedience,</hi> your zeale with <hi>iudgment,</hi> and your loue to <hi>religion,</hi> with your louing acceptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of religious <hi>vniformitie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Your Fathers at the Lawe, meaſuring the Lawes <hi>equitie</hi> by publicke vtilitie, doe condemne them for guiltie, which attempt to doe any thing contrary to <note place="margin">Smith. de repub. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> l. 1. cap. 2.</note> the Lawe, yea though it were to doe good: And with graue <hi>reſolution</hi> aſſure, that the <hi>King</hi> cannot alter and change the lawes of this <hi>Realme</hi> at his <note place="margin">Forteſc. in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend. of the lawes of Engl. pa. 25.</note> pleaſure, becauſe the rule of his gouerment is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie royall; but pollitick. If you cannot finde any preuiledge for the <hi>ſubiect</hi> at his pleaſure to diſobay, let your examplarie approbation of <hi>rites</hi> publickly eſtabliſhed, lead them in the performance of holye duties.</p>
               <p>You are reall ſpeakers, and the chiefeſt <hi>graduates</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Bartolus.</note> of your facultie haue the <hi>Prerogatiue</hi> of <hi>plea</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Actions, and therefore muſt more entend to the <note place="margin">Scire leges non eſt eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum verba tenere, ſed vim &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gula iuris.</note> things for which the Lawes are decreed, then to the words by which the Lawes are deliuered; yet whether you conſider the letter of the Lawe, or the reaſon, (which is the life of the Lawe ſaith <hi>Baldus,</hi> the ſpirit of the lawe ſaith <hi>Panormitan,</hi> and the bond that bindeth.) He that wreſteth the Lawe in one, doth offer wrong to the Lawe in the other, and by both, hath often times hindred the Church of her learned <hi>Miniſtrie,</hi> when the cauſe hath come to a <hi>Quare impedit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How much the Church hath heeretofore reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in her honourable helpe of profitable and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:14815:31"/> lawes, enacted by his <hi>Maieſties</hi> moſt noble <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors,</hi> the <hi>Kings</hi> of theſe famous <hi>Ilands,</hi> to protect her <hi>peace,</hi> and priuiledge her <hi>ſafetie,</hi> againſt Noue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts the vntimely enimies of moſt auncient times truth, her bleſſed <hi>mother</hi> on earth, and beſt beloued to her <hi>Father</hi> in heauen, the <hi>hiſtories</hi> of our venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>predeceſſors,</hi> doe reporte with <hi>memorable</hi> teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of their bleſſed names. Let me onely tell you, the <hi>Church</hi> now (comforted with the pleaſefull aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, and ſtrengthened with the powerfull hand of his Maieſtie) hopefully expecteth, that as in <hi>pleading</hi> our cauſes, your legall Philoſophie, is free from <note place="margin">Didimus ad Alexan.</note> thoſe rules which the <hi>Philoſophy ſchooles</hi> doe allowe their diſputants (with falſated ſpeeches to couer vntruthes) ſo you vouchſafe her the true Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of your generous freedome, moſt demonſtratiue in your <hi>Obedience,</hi> to her holy <hi>preſcriptions</hi> and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian lawes of out moſt Chriſtian <hi>King,</hi> if ſhe may obtaine this, but reaſonable and honeſt <hi>boone</hi> at your hands, who are profeſſors of the Lawe, by obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her <hi>rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> in your <hi>Churches, Chappels,</hi> and Oratories, your ſuch practiſe will be her preſeruatiue, and her prayers a bleſſing to your ſuch practiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>§. 16.</head>
               <p>Your Actions of <hi>ſingularitie,</hi> are in ſuch ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all veneration, with your vnlearned retinue, that you cannot now leaue them without remorce,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14815:31"/> hauing vſed them with ſo great applauſe, nor well reclaime your followers from thoſe giddie follyes, which with ſuch force you haue laboured to indeede vnto their conceipts.</p>
               <p>There is no opinion ſo fantaſticall, nor fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie <note place="margin">A nullis conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinibus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo diffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius auelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ab his quae ad opinionem pertinent. Orige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. l. 1. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra. celſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> ſo extrauagant, but if cuſtome ſet the foote of her Authoritie in vs, reaſon cannot remoue the <hi>impoſture,</hi> the deepe and ſenſible impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Libertie</hi> will not admit reaſonable perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and ſo long as your affections lye couered vnder that ſtone, they cannot plye to the rule which truth affordes, and vnderſtanding would adminiſter.</p>
               <p>Howbeit, where the feare of the Lawe is, there <note place="margin">Chriſoſt. ho. 14. ad pop. Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chenum.</note> cuſtome is eaſilie broken, and for that this ruſt hath eaten into you through their <hi>ſufferance,</hi> who by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandation from Soueraigntie haue receaued in charge the execution of the Lawes ordained for the ſtrengthfull maintenance of this both Eccleſiaſticall and Ciuill pollicie.</p>
               <p>I truſt you (my Lordes the Iudges of the land) which haue the iudgements of our cauſes, the cenſure of our <hi>behauiour,</hi> and ſentence of our Actions, will ſo take to hart the defence of theſe dutyes (in performance whereof reſteth the very <hi>Soule</hi> of our Church, and life of Churches flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing,) that neyther greatneſſe of Authoritie, nor power of perſon, nor eminencie of place, nor loue of <hi>fauourites,</hi> nor fancie to <hi>faction,</hi> ſhall cauſe you to winke at, or diſpence with any, eyther
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:14815:32"/> 
                  <hi>Anabaptisticallie</hi> ſpirited, or ſeditiouſlie oppoſite, to this pure and vnſtained religion, by Lawe eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed.</p>
               <p>The vnpartiall defence of this, claimeth the firſt place aboue all, whatſoeuer <hi>Soueraigntie</hi> hath co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionated vnto your Authoritie, as well in regard of the care which earth <hi>iudging</hi> vpon earth, ought <note place="margin">Auſt. ſer. 94.</note> to haue of his iudgement which iudgeth in the <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens,</hi> as alſo for the happy aduauncement of publick good, which ebbeth or floweth as God the Author of all good is reſpectiuely ſerued. For proofe of this.</p>
               <p>If you looke vpon the bleſſings wherewith the giuer of all Prerogatiues, hath proſperouſlie enri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched this <hi>Nation,</hi> eyther in warlike action, or peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able deliberation, you ſhall ſee them flowe from the ſpring of <hi>humble obedience</hi> towards true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; or if you pleaſe to beholde them darkned in their wiſdome, <hi>hart-fallen</hi> in their courage, <hi>amazed</hi> in their ſpirits, <hi>confounded</hi> in their councels, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken in the iſſues of their owne conſultations, you may diſcrie the vapoures of their vnhappineſſe, ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from their backwardneſſe in performing thoſe moſt excellent and moſt deſerued dutyes, which God by the <hi>Miniſtrie</hi> of his Church had preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, and <hi>Princes</hi> zealous of diuine glorye com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded.</p>
               <p>In conſideration whereof, the <hi>Church</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weale, are moſt earneſt <hi>obteſtants,</hi> that as you are <hi>Agents</hi> for God, in the Adminiſtration of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and <hi>iusticed</hi> by the <hi>King</hi> (their <hi>ſupreame</hi> head
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:14815:32"/> and <hi>Soueraigne</hi> defender) to execute the <hi>iudgments</hi> of God, the hand of Iuſtice, guided by the eyes of your wiſdome, may ſecure them from the ſmartfull <hi>inconueniences</hi> of Atheiſticall ſecuritie, and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then them in their <hi>mutuall</hi> Offices againſt their <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſticall</hi> oppoſites, whoſe mindes diuorſed from dutie, doe ſtiftly refuſe the rules of our religious du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, proudly cenſure the validitie and priuitie of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraignes gouerment,</hi> Odiouſlie calumniate the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious function of holy <hi>Prieſthood;</hi> wilfullie ſhake of, thoſe good things which authoritie hath enacted to eſtabliſh common good; cunningly indeauour by ſhouldering out the Liturgey and holy <hi>Hymnes,</hi> to bring the worſhip of God with vs to a meere <hi>preach,</hi> and contentiouſlie hinder the perfection of that <hi>v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie,</hi> which would make them with vs religious to God, humble to the Church, loyall to our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, and louingly peacefull amongſt our ſelues, if they did not hinder it.</p>
               <p>In all theſe actiue and mouing errours of their deceiued mindes, what elſe haue they aymed at, but to wrong this body polliticke, through contempt of the lawes both of <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>iuſtice,</hi> both which, you may ſee dayly violated with contemptuous brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; that of <hi>honour,</hi> by affected <hi>derogation</hi> from Soueraigntie; the other of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> by ſtrong inforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their priuate fancie; and when the <hi>miſhaped</hi> diſorder of ſome few, ſhall diſtemper the welformed feature of the whole body, when <hi>affectation</hi> of ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laritie, ſhall with <hi>vnreſtraineable</hi> and head-long courſe of violent <hi>Schiſme,</hi> teare in ſunder the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeamed
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14815:33"/> 
                  <hi>coate</hi> of Chriſt, when audacious <hi>ignorance</hi> ſhall call into queſtion the lawfull <hi>Ordinances,</hi> which ripeſt iudgment hath decreed: the <hi>fancies</hi> of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate men, <hi>wantonized</hi> with conceipt of <hi>purietic,</hi> ſhall not onely denie their <hi>Obedience</hi> in holy offices, law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully impoſed, but with <hi>clamorous inuectiues</hi> traduce their honourable reputation, whoſe place doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyne them to ſee the obſeruation of that which Lawe hath appointed;) what may we elſe looke for my <hi>Lords)</hi> but that proude <hi>popularitie</hi> giue the checke to <hi>monarchie,</hi> and prophane <hi>vanitie</hi> doe weaken <hi>pietie,</hi> if your zeale for the Lawes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto your truſt, doe not adde <hi>validitie</hi> to <note place="margin">1. Eliz. cap. 2. 23. Eliz. cap. 1.</note> ſtrenthen them, and feare from your hand by their due execution, teach vs <hi>obedience</hi> in the workes of <hi>deuotion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the ſollemne Actions of your Iudgment, thoſe ſutable <hi>ornaments,</hi> your <hi>robe,</hi> your <hi>cloake,</hi> your <hi>coife,</hi> are a beautie, and are the comelie veſtures wherewith deuoute liberalitie hath apparrelled <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> a ſtaine vnto her.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Priestly</hi> habite deuiſed and vſed by <hi>Priests</hi> of olde, to celebrate the Actions of diuine worſhip with <hi>ſolempnitie,</hi> and giue ſtate vnto their <hi>Seſsions</hi> when determination of <hi>Ciuill</hi> cauſes, had dependant <hi>reference</hi> vnto their iudgement, is an <hi>enſigne</hi> of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour vnto you (my <hi>Lords)</hi> and will retaine it aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent excellencie, without imputation of blemiſh; or note of blame, to the firſt deuiſers, if you vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe the Church this fauour, to tender the <hi>magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence</hi> of her ſeruice, now the cognition of her
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:14815:33"/> cauſes in that kind is deuolued vnto you as Church men were formerly carefull, to ſet forth the <hi>mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence</hi> of your place and calling.</p>
               <p>Sith then you haue receaued thoſe <hi>abiliments</hi> from the Church, and the world taketh ſpeciall knowledge of your high place by the honorable <hi>enſigments</hi> of your ſuch <hi>habitts?</hi> Suffer not <hi>Nouelty</hi> to diſhonour the Church in that wherein you are honored. Leaue her not to goe naked that hath cloathed you, but ſo <hi>negotiate</hi> her affaires in your <hi>Circuits</hi> and <hi>Seſsions,</hi> that her ſeruice in the <hi>Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary</hi> may be performed with due and comely <hi>exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This if you doe, you ſhall remoue occaſion of offence, taken by contrariety of <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> you ſhall giue the holy <hi>worde</hi> and <hi>Sacraments</hi> a better relliſh in their Iudgements who for the obſeruation of ſome few <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> do ſo much diſtaſte them, at a word you ſhall giue a bleſsing of <hi>happineſse</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this <hi>Church,</hi> if by one vniforme religious obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of things commanded, as behooufull to Gods ſeruice, you keepe vs one in the bonde of deuine worſhip. A bleſsing not to be looked for in a <hi>Babilonicall</hi> confuſion, which preſumeth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide and quarter a tongue of one ſpeach, but in the Church of God which retayneth the <hi>Vnity</hi> of the ſpirit in the bonde of <hi>peace.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:14815:34"/>
               <head>§. 17</head>
               <p>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Tanta eſt in repub de morú vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etate diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitas: vt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo valeat leges defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere niſi terror vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deatur ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perare. Caſſiodor. 12. variaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> epiſt.</note> It was a rule alwayes obſerued by them who were <hi>good-husbands</hi> for the common-wealth, that what vntractable men doe not vpon <hi>admonition,</hi> they muſt he inforced vnto by <hi>compulſion,</hi> howbeit (his <hi>greatneſſe)</hi> knowing that <note n="b" place="margin">Prou. 20. Quaere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dae ſunt ignoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendi cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſae non pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niendi oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſiones. Ammianus Marcelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus. l. 19. Procla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 16. Iulij. 1604 Lex ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet vim co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentem. Ariſt. l. 10. Eth. c. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>pietie</hi> and <hi>mercie</hi> are the pillars of Princely rule, the chiefeſt dowrie that God giues vnto <hi>Kings,</hi> and precious <hi>ornament</hi> of <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> more deſirous of cauſe to pardon, then of occaſion to puniſh, doth earneſtly wiſh there may neuer occaſion be giuen to make proofe of <hi>ſeueritie,</hi> but that his Princely <hi>declarations</hi> may haue equall force in all mens harts, to worke an vniuerſall <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie,</hi> by clemencie and weight of reaſon, not by conſtraint and rigour of Lawe.</p>
               <p>It is in his power to make himſelfe <hi>feared,</hi> he choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth rather to make himſelfe beloued, which <hi>loue-full</hi> dutie, if it were ſo happily performed by vs, as by him is <hi>highlie</hi> merited, his Maieſtie ſhould alwayes finde your <hi>concurrencie</hi> with him in the worke of Gods ſeruice; and you ſhould neuer feele that <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitizing</hi> diſpoſition which the Lawe hath towards thoſe who are <hi>reſractorie</hi> and <hi>repugnant</hi> to this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of ſeruice.</p>
               <p>The power of the Lawe-maker (and the <hi>Lawe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Plutar. Plato.</note> is the worke of the <hi>King,</hi> to whoſe regall <hi>dignitie</hi> it appertaines to make <hi>Lawes)</hi> ſhould breed a feare in our harts, how we ſpeake or iudge in the worſt part
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:14815:34"/> concerning that, the vnaduiſed diſgrace whereof may be no meane diſhonour to him, towards whom we profeſſe all <hi>ſubmiſsion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By <hi>excommunication</hi> to be ſhut out of the Church, and bebarred of fellowſhip in holy duties, is a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection more ſmartfull then that you ſhould wilfully deſerue it, and ſo due to your <hi>diſobedience,</hi> that he which will not acknowledge the more then <hi>mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie</hi> power of the Church, may not enioy the preui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <note place="margin">Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius. Pontifex.</note> of a child, to be nouriſhed in the bowels and boſome of the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dereliction</hi> of your <hi>Paſtorall</hi> cures will be ſo bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſome to your <hi>ſoules,</hi> obliged vnto them with ſo ſtrickt a bond of <hi>conſcience,</hi> and hurtfull to the <hi>Church</hi> which requireth your <hi>Miniſteriall</hi> imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to aduance the purchaſe of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> that you ought with principall care to attend that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto the holy <hi>ghoſt</hi> hath ſeperated you.</p>
               <p>Depriuation from the roomes of your ſpirituall <hi>functions,</hi> wherevnto you haue had ſo <hi>honourable</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance, will imprint your <hi>diſobedience</hi> with a full ſtaine of diſgrace vnto your <hi>obſtinacie,</hi> but cleare the <hi>Luſtre</hi> of gouerment from thoſe too many diſgraces, wherewith your obſtinate diſobedience hath labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſtaine it.</p>
               <p>That is not a lawfull <hi>Miniſtrie</hi> (ſaith Maiſter <note place="margin">2. p. 2. repl. pa. 167.</note> 
                  <hi>Cartwright,)</hi> that is obſtinate, and where the <hi>obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacie</hi> is generall, or for the moſt part, there the <hi>State</hi> is ruinous, ſo that the <hi>Prince</hi> may after due meanes aſſayed to bring them <hi>home,</hi> procure that other be put in their places.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:14815:35"/>
               <p>\ You will thinke this is much <hi>ſeueritie,</hi> but the Lawe preſumeth the extreamitie of your diſcent, whereby you labour to blemiſh what his wiſdome hath polliſhed, and <hi>authoritie</hi> publiſhed: Therefore if you feele his power as a ſtrong rocke which <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorgeth</hi> the <hi>inuectiue waues</hi> that ſtrike againſt it; blame your ſelues.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>§. 18.</head>
               <p>To ſubmit the publick <hi>conſtitutions</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> to the <hi>inſtabilitie</hi> of priuate fancie, no pollicie did euer tollerate, no not in the <hi>ciuill</hi> Lawe, where the reaſon of man hath moſt familier commerce: how can you then (the <hi>Brethren</hi> of this <hi>faction)</hi> expect <hi>tolleration</hi> in matters of ſo great importance, or conceaue any reaſon, that your priuate reaſon, (which is a priuate iuriſdiction) ſhould euer rule in things diuine, ſo farre aboue the reach of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon apprehention.</p>
               <p>You ſee the rule of his <hi>Highneſſe gouernment</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Lex ex ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo ad omnes pertinent Arch. l. de lege &amp; iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitia.</note> doth extend to all after a like meaſure: and ſith he hath <hi>authoritie</hi> of <hi>ſupreame</hi> commaund ouer all, in fauour of whome ſhould he remitte any part of his <hi>Soueraigntie,</hi> I doe with all <hi>humilitie</hi> acknowledge his <hi>Maieſties</hi> royall power, to diſpence with his Lawes, as in wiſdome he ſhall thinke moſt condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent to the good of that pollitique body (whoſe head God hath made him,) but if he ſhould yeeld the bridle, and giue you leaue to ſhroude your ſelues in the boſome of his <hi>protection,</hi> and by his Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:14815:35"/> ſhelter your <hi>nouelties</hi> from the rigour of the law, what profit ſhould we reape. Sure I am that ſuch paſſionate <hi>ſurprizing</hi> of Princely <hi>deſignements</hi> will more trouble then ſteed the quiet repoſe of the Church; and aſſoone may you erect <hi>Colonies</hi> in the <hi>Moone</hi> for the vſe, as by your <hi>nouelties</hi> bring any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit to the common-wealth. The <hi>ſufference</hi> which you haue already gained, hath hitherto perplexed both <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>common-wealth</hi> with many diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, and would vnauoidable caſt vs into ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>incombrances,</hi> if this rule of pollicie had not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed; it is better to preuent, then to bee preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p>Compleat <hi>vnion</hi> is of better conſequence to the furtherance of <hi>Religion,</hi> then that admittance ſhould be giuen to any example which leadeth from it, and your knowne diſpoſition <hi>contumeliouſly</hi> to traduce them, who looke not the ſame way that you doe, hath beene more violent and virulent then any ingenious <hi>ſpirit</hi> may willingly complie with.</p>
               <p>You could neuer as yet with a ſingle eye looke at the <hi>ſtate</hi> oppoſite to the opinion you holde, and gouerment you ſeeke for: and it is to be feared, that your zeale which rideth with ſo hotte a ſpurre beſide the <hi>cauſway</hi> of <hi>Obedience,</hi> will not omitte any occurrent that may procure you the equall free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of that which you call <hi>conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is out of queſtion, that if you might once gaine <hi>permiſsion,</hi> to reiect thoſe things wherof the lawes, or reuerence of <hi>auncient</hi> cuſtome, hath in fomer times made impreſſion, you would not thence-forwarde
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:14815:36"/> allowe of any thing, but what you your ſelues ſhall firſt giue voice and perticular conſent vnto.</p>
               <p>They were your teachers which account thoſe <note place="margin">Cartw. 2. p. of his 2. repl. pa 65.</note> Princes who are <hi>not refined</hi> by their ſpirite, vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be accounted amongſt the number of men, and therefore rather to be ſpitted vpon then obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. They were your teachers which defend rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt Princes of a different religion, and honor thoſe that are ſlaine in ſuch quarrels with the glory of <hi>martyrs.</hi> They were your teachers which vtterly <note place="margin">Buccanam de Iure regni apud Scotos. pa 70.</note> miſlike, that Princes ſhould be exempted from <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall</hi> diſcipline, and namely from <hi>excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> They were your teachers who haue ſentenced that <hi>Prince</hi> to be vnworthy of <hi>life</hi> vpon the earth, who by cenſure of excommunication is caſt into hell.</p>
               <p>Theſe dangerous <hi>poſitions</hi> are to me like ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie fearefull <hi>foreſhewes</hi> of an vndoubted aſſurance, that if your <hi>democraty</hi> might haue taken place, (for you moue and remoue in your <hi>motions</hi> by the ſame ſprings and wardes) his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> ſhould quickly haue loſt the obedience, and found the <hi>vexation</hi> of ſeditious Subiects. <hi>Commaundement</hi> ſhould be no longer his weapon, where ſuch <hi>Commaunders</hi> haue place of charge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <head>§. 19.</head>
               <p>But you will leaue your charge, although <hi>Beza</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Diſcourſe of troub. at Frankf. pa. 202. &amp; 206</note> and others of <hi>Geneua,</hi> doe wiſh you rather to giue ouer your functions to open wrong, and retire your
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:14815:36"/> ſelfe from theſe things commaunded, vnto your pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate life. Yet <hi>Cartwright</hi> dare not be author vnto any of you, to forſake his paſtorall charge for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience of a <hi>Surpliſse,</hi> his reaſon is, for that the one is an abſolute commaundement of the Lord, and <note place="margin">2. p. 2. repl. pa. 264.</note> the other a thing of his owne <hi>nature</hi> indifferent, which being layde in the <hi>ballance</hi> with the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the worde, is of leſſe importance then for the refuſall of it, you ſhould forgoe ſo neceſſarie a dutie.</p>
               <p>You heare the iudgement of a Maiſter in your <hi>ſchoole,</hi> and if you be not carried with too much auer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from the auncient <hi>fathers</hi> (who knew not your <hi>ſchoole)</hi> accept this argument taken both from the one, and from the other.</p>
               <p>The preaching of the <hi>worde,</hi> is ſo neceſſary for him <note place="margin">Cartvv.</note> that is called thereunto; that a woe hangeth on his head that doth not preach, but where the holy <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ierom. m, prouerb.</note> denounceth a woe, it notes a mortall ſinne in that which followes; therfore to forgoe your ſuch charge, is to tranſporte your ſelues into the very bulke of ſinne, and mortallitie to ſinne.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Scamo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny</hi> is too fretting, yet, will not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende your ſtomackes if you take it, as it is giuen with <hi>Quinces,</hi> my moderate affections, vnwilling to grieue you, and ſo taking it, my hope is that you will not omitte the principall and ſubſtantiall part of your duties, for ſhaddowes and ſemblances of zeale, but bend your ſtrength, with his Highneſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, to ioyne in one againſt the comon aduerſary, for the eſtabliſhing of the goſpell.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:14815:37"/>
               <p>\ You are credited with the free diſpoſition of Gods ineſtimable benefits, and therefore will not (being as I hope you are thoſe good guiding Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, you ſoe earneſtly ſpeake for,) ſhrinke from your miniſtery, or decline from the worke whereunto you are called.</p>
               <p>If you be <hi>Salt,</hi> ſeaſon, if <hi>lights,</hi> ſhine, if <hi>guides,</hi> goe before, and as the Apoſtolike fathers of former time, did by there labour make many, of prophane, holy, of <hi>ignorant,</hi> learned, of obſtinate ſinners, penitent conuerts, ſo doe you endeauour that by your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry others may change their affections, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their <hi>manners</hi> towards God, with reuerence to performe their outward religious offices, <hi>Contempt of religious dutie, argues an irreligious contempt of deitie</hi> towards the Church, with humilitie, to conforme themſelues to her holy ordinances in the ſeruice of god, where dutie is <hi>ſubmiſsion,</hi> oppoſition betokens <hi>pride,</hi> towards the Kinge, with loyaltie to yeelde o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience vnto his lawes. <hi>A wilfull Lawbreaker, would willingly breake the Lawgiuer</hi> towards religion, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently clothing themſelues with the garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and redily caſting of euery oppoſite thing that might hinder them in the exerciſe of chriſtian duties.</p>
               <p>It is a manifeſt wrong offered to <hi>Religion</hi> when the outward action doth not conſent &amp; ſimpathize with the affected profeſsion, for albeit, <hi>faith</hi> doth giue faſhion and worth vnto workes, yet workes giue the true tincture and luſtre vnto faith. (wherefore I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you and in the bowels of Chriſt I beſeech you,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:14815:37"/> affect the excellencie of conſtant courſe in the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of thoſe things which belonge vnto your <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry,</hi> ſuffer not a matter of meere <hi>formalitie,</hi> to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſt the performance of your duty, but ſubmit your ſelues vnto the wiſdome of <hi>Authoritie,</hi> and becauſe you plead for your ſelues <hi>ingenuity</hi> of ſpirit, your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended leader vnto theſe things; ſtriue to tend to that which is moſt exquiſit in euery <hi>ingenious</hi> ſpirit, truth in your opinion, vertue in your action, and peace in your conuerſation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>§. 20.</head>
               <p>There is nothing more behoouful for the vſe of life &amp; ſeruice of publike ſociety, then to proportion this ſhady &amp; <hi>terreſtrial</hi> life to that moſt happy &amp; celeſtial, where <hi>Angells</hi> the moſt induſtrious attendants one the <hi>ſupernall</hi> Maieſtie, and truly faithfull <hi>guardions</hi> of our much endangered ſaffety, doe in the perfection of their obedience to God their <hi>immortall King</hi> in heauen, ſet downe to vs, the <hi>Idea</hi> of Loue, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and duty to the <hi>King our mortall God</hi> vpon Earth.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Rex orat. habita in Senat.</note> Of Loue, with loue to repay that royall loue wherein his <hi>Highneſse</hi> doth more glory in our weale, then in his owne perticular aduantage, and with inſeperable <hi>Vnion</hi> to Crowne the beauty of our Loue, ſo viſibly apprehenſiue in the ſhine of his Glory.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">In princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes veluti parentes beneuolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia nos af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectos eſſe decet. obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientes et venerantes. nam patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni ſunt ac domini ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitatis &amp; ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uium ſalut. Charondas in proemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is legum.</note> Of <hi>Honor,</hi> humblye to acknowledge his <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame</hi> ſoueraignty in the ſuper-eminent excellencie,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:14815:38"/> whereof, as he hath greateſt conformitie with God, ſo he cleareth the euidence of his greatneſſe and potencie, to effect thoſe delectable and deſirable good things, which haue their dependencie vpon his greatneſſe.</p>
               <p>Of <hi>dutie,</hi> cheerefully to performe the offices of our ſeuerall functions, by the law proportioned, as they doe the exerciſe of their high and admirable vertues, to the glory of <hi>God,</hi> and good of men.</p>
               <p>They hould inuiolable the bond of <hi>fellowſhip,</hi> wherin they are aſſociated we ſhould keepe faſt the <hi>Linkes</hi> of Chriſtian <hi>ſocietie,</hi> wherein we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bined by communitie of ſeruice, and perticipation of <hi>Sacraments,</hi> they vndeceauable aſſurances of Gods bleſſings, the <hi>vnualuable</hi> pledges of Chriſt his goodneſſe, and venerable warrants of our future <hi>bleſſedneſſe</hi> in <hi>Angelicall</hi> happineſſe.</p>
               <p>They neuer incline to remit any part of their dutie, we ſhould not permit any eyther coulour of <hi>pleaſure,</hi> or baite of <hi>follie,</hi> or pretext of <hi>fauour,</hi> or vaile of <hi>Sanctitie,</hi> to auert our conceipt from perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of thoſe offices which by our owne conſent, and heauens immediate appointment, he hath power to commaund vs: but as they doe althings to fulfill, and keepe the Lawe of the Almightie, we ſhould order the Actions of our liues vnto his Maieſties iuſt <hi>Commaunds,</hi> the correſpondence which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Actions of men in this eſtate of our mortallitie, and their heauenly operations of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, doth require theſe things of all in generall, but
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:14815:38"/> eſpecially of vs who muſt appeare for others in the preſence of God as Angels.</p>
               <p>When the Church of God was attended on by thoſe <hi>Apoſtolique Fathers,</hi> whoſe induſtrious tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile in the buſineſſe of the Church, did <hi>gaine</hi> them the names of <hi>Angels,</hi> althings were carefullie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed for rhe continuation of the <hi>Catholicke peace.</hi> In their <hi>Councels</hi> they determined all matters of doubt or difficultie which might diſturbe the peace of the Church, and what they determined was no more controuerted.</p>
               <p>In their <hi>Synods,</hi> they prouided by holy ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances to reforme all <hi>treſpaſſes</hi> repugnant to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient holy <hi>Cannons:</hi> and what they ordained was cheerfully obſerued.</p>
               <p>In their <hi>Sermons,</hi> they laboured with graue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations to keepe their ſubiects in due allegance vnto their temporall <hi>Lords,</hi> and what they councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led was religiouſlie regarded.</p>
               <p>In their Actions, they did with reuerent <hi>humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie</hi> make knowne their ſubiection to Chriſtian <hi>Princes:</hi> And Chriſtian Princes (amongſt whom <note place="margin">Religio &amp; iuſtitia po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litica mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuis ſtant non ſolum officiis ſed beneficijs.</note> our Soueraigne doth aſſociate with moſt honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reſolution) eſteeming nothing dearer then reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, moſt willingly imployed their Authoritie to aduance all religious Actions, and prouide for the Churches ſafetie by <hi>oppoſition to noueltie.</hi> The mutuall <hi>reciprocation</hi> of theſe Chriſtian offices was then the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of their <hi>gouerment,</hi> the <hi>Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtarre</hi> of their happineſſe, the Centor of their Peace,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:14815:39"/> And will be to vs that ſo much ſpoken of, and much deſired <hi>mother</hi> of our <hi>goulden</hi> world.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <head>§. 21.</head>
               <p>The thoughtfull remembrance of this doth giue me hart to ſpeake vnto you <hi>(Right reuerend Fathers)</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. ad vbi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxos.</note> and to requeſt, as bleſſed <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> did thoſe of his time, ſo to ſtrengthen your mindes in the liuely emotions of chriſtian zeale, (the <hi>Garment</hi> that beautifieth the <hi>Stewards</hi> of Gods diuine <hi>miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,)</hi> that thoſe good things which the Church of God, hath hitherto happily enioyed, may not in your times vnhappilie be diſcontinued.</p>
               <p>Many attempts haue ben made by many, (whoſe actions do witneſſe they are impatient of gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, apt to <hi>tumult,</hi> zealous of nothing more then their owne conceipts, though they be as the are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warranted by truth, diſclaimed by <hi>Antiquitie,</hi> indeede the <hi>Muſhroomes</hi> of yeſterdayes <hi>Nouelty)</hi> many attempts I ſay, haue bene made to deface the beauty of the Church, and weaken her ſtrength, by weakning your gouerment. If their malice had bene ſo forcible, as it was induſtrious, and their <hi>Appellations</hi> ſo regardfully accepted, as they were violently vrged, your <hi>Authority,</hi> your <hi>Dignitie</hi> ſhould not now bene queſtioned, but they ſhould not now haue bene.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:14815:39"/>
               <p>\ You haue hitherto with fatherly care, reſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned your ſelues from the ſeuere execution of lawes made againſt them, and meere compaſſion hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed you to reſtraine your ſelues; if the Church, whoſe rulers you are, had gayned a reſtraint of their vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall contradictions againſt the <hi>State,</hi> warranted with a ſetled <hi>Vnion</hi> of affection to the <hi>State,</hi> your firſt <hi>Lenity</hi> had bene well imployed: and their obedient humilitie preuented the motion which now their continuing repugnancie, doth force from vs, for your due cenſure of their vndutiful <hi>recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſancie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The continuance whereof, they cannot impute vnto any weaknes, orinſuffie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie in the meanes which haue beene vſed towardes them, but to the willful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of their obſtinate harts againſt the meanes which haue beene vſed; with mindes obdurate no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing preuayleth.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Oratione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quae nobis co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>di eſt, facile com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probare ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemus. Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noras anu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al. cap. vlt.</note> You haue entreated them gently; but the ſpeach that pleaſeth not hath not allowance: <note n="b" place="margin">Apud no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentis ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis ſit eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens ratio, haec ipſa obſtaculu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe ſolet. Greg: epiſt. 41. l. 3.</note> You haue reaſoned with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but to their vnwilling minds, <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> it ſelfe, be it neuer ſo euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, is oftimes a <hi>hindera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</hi> 
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendi mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus nullus erit reſpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dend. eſſe reſpondent. ſemper ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtimamus. Auſtin.</note> You haue anſwered their bookes, but your <hi>conte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation</hi> hath the more engaged them to oppoſition, You haue giuen them fatherly <hi>Councels,</hi> and had they carefully applyed your Councells vnto their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to follow them, as they haue vnprofitablie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended them vnto their memories only to croſſe them, they might haue bene able to diſtinguiſh, the true viſage of a truly reformed <hi>Church</hi> amongſt vs.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:14815:40"/>
               <p>\ Your <hi>clemency</hi> hath omitted no reaſonable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements that might any way be auaileable to ioyne their ſubmiſsion vnto <hi>authorized</hi> proceedings, if neither courteſie of vſage, nor force of reaſon, can ſtoppe the current of their conceipts. <hi>Authority muſt procure what vertue can not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The goodneſſe of <hi>nature</hi> it ſelfe enclineth more to mildeneſſe then rigour, and the Church deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth with moderate and mercifull courſes, rather then ſeuere <hi>inforcements</hi> to aduance the obſeruation of her ſpirituall <hi>ordinances.</hi> The holy fathers <hi>Gregorie</hi> at <hi>Nazianzen</hi> &amp; <hi>Auſten</hi> at <hi>Hippo;</hi> did acknowledge it: How be it finding by experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in the <hi>Arrians, Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Auſt. l. 2. retract. c. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Appollinariſts,</hi> &amp; other froward oppoſites vnto the Church <hi>Catholique,</hi> that Preſumption makes men in loue <hi>with their errours,</hi> and impunitie doth foſter preſumption, they then thought requiſite by practiſe of <hi>diſcipline,</hi> to accompliſh what they could not effect by <hi>doctrine:</hi> And better with moderate ſeueritie to correct them which diſturbe the <hi>Peace</hi> of the Church with vnhallowed <hi>contentions,</hi> then by ſuffering in conformitie vnto good lawes to giue paſſage vnto confuſion.</p>
               <p>Diſobedient mindes are more eaſilie taught when the feare of <hi>ſeueritie</hi> doth ſecond the induſtrious <note place="margin">Auſt. epiſt. 184.</note> 
                  <hi>Schoolemaiſters</hi> of truth, inſomuch that <hi>Saint Ierome</hi> wondered at that Biſhop who ſuffered <hi>Vigilantius</hi> to reſt in his <hi>iuriſdiction,</hi> and would not with his <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicall</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ierem l. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigilantiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> rod breake ſo vnprofitable a veſſell.</p>
               <p>You know <hi>(honorable and reuerend Fathers,)</hi> that we are a <hi>Spectacle</hi> to God, to Angells, and to men,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:14815:40"/> the good the bad, the weake; <hi>God</hi> requireth the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of our ſeruice, according to the <hi>high</hi> of his excellencies, and will not ſuffer himſelfe to be mocked with <hi>Copper</hi> for <hi>Golde, Glaſſe</hi> for <hi>pearle, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming</hi> for <hi>being,</hi> or <hi>fancy</hi> for <hi>conſcience,</hi> but claymeth the vttermoſt of the ability which our vnfained af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections towards him may yeeld; if poſsiblie we could yeeld him ſo much, as his diuine <hi>ſublimitie</hi> deſerueth when it is rightly conſidered.</p>
               <p>Angells attend the furtherance of our religious duties, to preſent them before God, and repreſent his fauour towards them.</p>
               <p>To this end, that we remembring the royall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue of our chriſtian ſoules, ſerued by their <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall miniſtrye</hi> and heauens bleſſed acceptation of our religious duties, beautified with <hi>correſpondencie</hi> to heauens glory, may remember to performe them with that <hi>ſolempnity</hi> which beſt beſeemeth the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>religion,</hi> and hath moſt concurrency with their celeſtiall exerciſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Good men,</hi> reioyce that the church is ſo gratiouſly preſerued from the baſeneſſe of <hi>nouelty,</hi> and do zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly wiſh that in euery chriſtian aſſembly, might be ſeene the cheerefull deuotion and bountious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences of thoſe religious fathers, who carried with a holy loue (like ſo many pleaſant <hi>Gales</hi> of wind blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the ayre, pointing vs to the <hi>hauen,</hi> and direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vs to the <hi>poynt</hi> whereto vnload the profits of our flitting life,) did enrich, endowe, and poſſeſſe holy men, holy religion, holy places, with much, with large, with great both goods, preuiledges, and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:14815:41"/> offering vp themſelues, and theirs, to furniſh the worſhip of God with a ſenſible excellency, the true <hi>teſtimony</hi> to God of their inward piety.</p>
               <p>This excellencie highly diſpleaſeth others, as if God more delighted with <hi>beggery,</hi> then <hi>bountie,</hi> and were better pleaſed to ſee <hi>Pellagius</hi> ſtanding before <note place="margin">Ierom. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſ. Pella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium. l. 1. c. 9.</note> him in a ſlouenlie coate, then <hi>Aaron</hi> in a decent veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Pompeis</hi> Horſes in a <hi>Stable</hi> by the <hi>Aulter,</hi> then the Diuine <hi>Sacrifices</hi> whereunto it was dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated. <hi>Iulian</hi> ſpoyling, then <hi>Conſtantine</hi> enriching <note place="margin">Theod. l. 2. cap. 24.</note> the Church. <hi>Sabellius</hi> ſitting Malancholy, then <hi>Baſill</hi> making melody vnto the Lord in ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <note place="margin">Baſil. epiſt. ad Neoce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar. 63.</note> all <hi>Hymnes. Cayne</hi> ſeruing him with the worſt, then <hi>Abell</hi> ſacrificing the beſt, And more accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the leane <hi>Oblations</hi> of a ſparing hand, then the liberall contributions of a Cheerefull gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</p>
               <p>Of all whatſoeuer Princely <hi>Munificence</hi> and chriſtian <hi>Zeale</hi> hath giuen to be Ornaments for the Church, and Arguments of their piety, you <hi>(ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Prelates</hi> (are the treaſurers to keepe it, the Ouerſeers to order it; and the <hi>Stewards</hi> to imploy it: If your fatherly care continue them vnto thoſe religious vſes; whereunto they were at firſt inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, it will nouriſh a reuerent affection in all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the Church to beautifie it, Religion to obſerue it, and your Order to Reuerence it.</p>
               <p>Wherefore now that the Church hath recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it ſelfe from the <hi>tempeſts</hi> and ſtormes of <hi>Newfang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſme,</hi> and diſcipline gayned the <hi>re-eſtabliſhment</hi> of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:14815:41"/> thoſe helpes wherein by longe diſturbance it hath bene much hindred (the <hi>ſupreame</hi> hand of diuine <hi>prouidence</hi> vphold his Throane in a bleſſed perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itie which hath done vs this good) let not the ſlack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned raynes of your <hi>regiment</hi> giue waye vnto pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane <hi>Liberty,</hi> teach the Obſtinate the execution of your <hi>Cannons,</hi> accept all occurrents that may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance the <hi>honour</hi> of his <hi>Crowne</hi> and <hi>dignity,</hi> who by his princly approbation hath giuen them the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of Lawes.</p>
               <p>They are the rules by which your <hi>Epiſcopall</hi> fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction muſt be directed, and the <hi>Obliquity</hi> of Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies diſpoſition rectified. The conſtant obſeruation of theſe, amongſt thoſe which are yours, will ground many reguler productions in the mindes of others. <note n="*" place="margin">Qui leges reipub, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culos eſſe dixerit, is perfecto nihil inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciauerit, que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enim res maxime neceſſaria animali no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> titubans o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus, ita reip. Legu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aequus &amp; rectus ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus. Leo imperat. conſtitut. 19.</note> They are the eyes by which your <hi>Iuſtice</hi> muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Actions of good men, to reward them, and to puniſh others. If theſe eyes be ſleepy, your <hi>conniuence</hi> will be their <hi>incouragement;</hi> who with the ſtroake of will, doe contend againſt the <hi>Streame</hi> of order.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Auſtin. l. 19. con. Fauſtum. ca. 11.</note> They are the <hi>Sinewes,</hi> by which religion, and her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rites are made of neere neighbours, that the Acts of religion cannot abſolutely be performed, if they want the furniture of comly ceremonies, nor the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies accounted ſacred, but as by religious ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration they ſerue to holy vſes.</p>
               <p>This ſhould make you more carefullie dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to reſtrayne the vncharitable Conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons made by priuate Men of your <hi>Canonicall</hi> reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to prouide that noe practiſe of <hi>Sathan,</hi>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:14815:42"/> nor fraude of <hi>hipocrites</hi> ſeperate what God and his church hath ſo neerely ioyned.</p>
               <p>Such do you bouldly forbid; be you afraid of <note place="margin">Chriſoſt. orat. de no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> contemne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da ecclesia dei, et diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rijs.</note> them, and they wil ſcorne you, doe you ſuffer them, and they will trouble you, though you want your <hi>Coſſier,</hi> you haue both rod and ſtaffe to repreſſe the inſolent, and ſtrengthen the weake, to conuert the incredulous, and rule the diſordered, to reclaime the <note place="margin">Barnard. l. 3. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider.</note> erronious, to convince ſeducers, and to bring them to amendment, or barre them liberty of deceipt.</p>
               <p>In performance of all which, your Epiſcopall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, bethinke your ſelues <hi>(my Lords)</hi> what the <hi>King,</hi> what his <hi>Councell,</hi> what the <hi>Country</hi> doth require of you, and if you be perſwaded that Heauen hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirited you, with this <hi>forme</hi> to extend the firſt <hi>frame,</hi> and aduance the ſucceſsiue parts of his church?</p>
               <p>If you ſtudie the glory of <hi>Chriſt</hi> your firſt <hi>Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Dioniſius. ca. 5. de Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erach ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtica.</note> who hath excellenced your order, with the rule of others, that by your rule, holy orders might be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued. If with due worſhippe you reuerence the <hi>aſperſion</hi> of his all-pacifing bloud, by which he hath ſet at one althings both in <hi>Heauen</hi> and <hi>Earth:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Col. 1. 20.</note> Seeke the peace of the Church by a well ordered <hi>concord</hi> of the Church, carry the hand of your <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> with an equall <hi>tenor,</hi> let not your actions ſwarue from your owne <hi>Cannons;</hi> what you haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to others, acknowledge it to be preſcribed to your ſelues. The <hi>authority</hi> of your place, the <hi>ſeruour</hi> of your zeale the <hi>grauity</hi> of your perſons, and <hi>light</hi> of your example, will grace your <hi>gouerment,</hi> and lead the <hi>Diſordered</hi> into the path of orders.</p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:14815:42"/>
               <p>\ Let your <hi>countenance</hi> be ſet vpon them, that are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious wirh a fatherly <hi>propenſion,</hi> encline to imbrace them, which frame the contexture of their ſeruice by the line of duty.</p>
               <p>Such as reclaime themſelues, cheriſh with the <hi>hopes</hi> of fauour, leaſt your ſtricktneſſe towards them, make others more obſtinate in their errors, and ſith that the double dyed mindes of ſome will not eaſily looſe their <hi>tincture,</hi> be ſpecially watchfull ouer the limiters of your Authority.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Finally</hi> ſo rule as you would be obayed, your <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall</hi> rule ſhall haue a <hi>canonicall obedience,</hi> and giue vs the harte of hope, that as his <hi>highneſse</hi> with prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>reſolution</hi> hath approoued this <hi>church,</hi> ſounde in <hi>Doctrine,</hi> decent in <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> perfect in <hi>Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and holy in her <hi>Liturgies,</hi> ſo he will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue her bleſſed in her <hi>peace,</hi> rich in her endowments, plentiful in her <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities,</hi> and free from the woundes of malice.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:14815:43"/>
            <head>Faults eſcaped.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>pag.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>lin.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Faults.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Correction.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>which interrupt</cell>
                     <cell>which may interrupt</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitting his owne</cell>
                     <cell>omitting his owne</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell>26</cell>
                     <cell>Maurilius</cell>
                     <cell>Mauritius</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell>guides-men</cell>
                     <cell>guides, men</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                     <cell>attributary</cell>
                     <cell>arbitrary</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>28</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>expectation</cell>
                     <cell>acceptation</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>32</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                     <cell>for ſeeking</cell>
                     <cell>forſaking</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                     <cell>ſtraying</cell>
                     <cell>ſtrayning</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>auntient times truth</cell>
                     <cell>auntiently times truth.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>51</cell>
                     <cell>26</cell>
                     <cell>of Churches</cell>
                     <cell>of our Churches</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>56</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                     <cell>by him is highly</cell>
                     <cell>by him it is highly</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>58</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>preſumeth</cell>
                     <cell>preſuppoſeth</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>ea.</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>ſhould euer rule</cell>
                     <cell>ſhould ouer rule</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>60</cell>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                     <cell>democraty</cell>
                     <cell>democracy</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>61</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>ſelfe from</cell>
                     <cell>ſelues from</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>ea.</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                     <cell>mortallity to ſinne</cell>
                     <cell>mortally to ſinne</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>63</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>formality to</cell>
                     <cell>formality cauſe you to</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>ea.</cell>
                     <cell>26</cell>
                     <cell>ſhine of his glory.</cell>
                     <cell>ſhine of his vertues.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>68</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>ioine their ſubmiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>winne their ſubmiſſion</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>ea.</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                     <cell>in conformity</cell>
                     <cell>vnconformitie</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>71</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>of neere neighbours</cell>
                     <cell>ſo neere neighbours</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>73</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>religious with a</cell>
                     <cell>religious with a</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>ea.</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>a canonicall</cell>
                     <cell>our canonicall</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14815:43"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
